<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Youths safety: or, Advice to the younger sort, of either sex More valuable than gold. Laying open the wicked practices of the town-shifts, sharpers, sharks, beau's, sweeteners, rakes, intreaging town-jilts, to cheat, ruin and disgrace gentlemen, shop-keepers, apprentices, gentlewomen, servant-maids, &amp;c. Serious reflections and good counsel, how they may know them, and avoid their snares. With their knavish-practices in gaming, and other matters worthy of note. By observation whereof, persons of either sex, may raise their fortunes. By J.W.</title>
            <author>J. W.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1698</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 152 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 45 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A67526</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing W76</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R219267</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99830759</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99830759</idno>
            <idno type="VID">35213</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A67526)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 35213)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1877:24)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Youths safety: or, Advice to the younger sort, of either sex More valuable than gold. Laying open the wicked practices of the town-shifts, sharpers, sharks, beau's, sweeteners, rakes, intreaging town-jilts, to cheat, ruin and disgrace gentlemen, shop-keepers, apprentices, gentlewomen, servant-maids, &amp;c. Serious reflections and good counsel, how they may know them, and avoid their snares. With their knavish-practices in gaming, and other matters worthy of note. By observation whereof, persons of either sex, may raise their fortunes. By J.W.</title>
                  <author>J. W.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 84 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Sold by E. Whitlock, near Stationers-Hall,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London] :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1698.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Place of publication from Wing.</note>
                  <note>At foot of title page: Price 6 d.</note>
                  <note>Gathered in 6's.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Rogues and vagabonds --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-07</date>
            <label>Lauren Proux</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-07</date>
            <label>Lauren Proux</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:35213:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:35213:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>Youths Safety: OR, ADVICE To the Younger Sort, of either Sex.</p>
            <p>More valuable than Gold.</p>
            <p>Laying open the Wicked Practices of the <hi>Town<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>Shifts, Sharpers, Sharks, Be<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>u's, Sweeteners, Rakes, Intreaging Town-Jilts,</hi> to Cheat, Ruin and Diſgrace Gentlemen, Shop-Keepers, Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prentices, Gentlewomen, Servant-Maids, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Serious Reflections and Good Counſel, how they may know them, and avoid their Snares. With their Knaviſh-Practices in Gaming, and other Matters worthy of Note.</p>
            <p>By Obſervation whereof, Perſons of either Sex, may raiſe their Fortunes.</p>
            <p>By <hi>J. W.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Sold by <hi>E. Whitlock,</hi> near <hi>Stationers-Hall,</hi> 1698. <hi>Price</hi> 6 <abbr>
                  <hi>d.</hi>
               </abbr>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:35213:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:35213:2"/>
            <head>
               <hi>Good and Sober Advice,</hi> TO THE YOUNGER SORT OF Either Sex, <hi>By way of Introduction.</hi>
            </head>
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. I.</head>
               <p>YOUTH is the Strength and Ornament of the Nation, and therefore great regard ought to be had to it, eſpecially in Culti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vating and ſeaſoning it with thoſe pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per Advantages and Qualifications that may render it comfortable in it ſelf, and conformable to the Publick Good. It is aptly Emblem'd by many things, as pliant Reeds, bending to the blaſts of eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry flattering Wind; by young <hi>Cupids,</hi> blowing Bubbles in the Air, and eagerly purſuing them, with a fondneſs of their Gaiety and various colours, till they break and vaniſh; by expanded Wax, whoſe ſoftneſs makes it liable to take any Impreſſion: And indeed, thoſe that come unfledged abroad, or too early into the World, have great need of ſober and
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:35213:3"/>ſound Advice, and to arm themſelves with precau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion for their ſafety, to preſerve their Reputation, Health and Fortunes: For let me plainly tell them, the World is treacherous and deceitful, and they almoſt every where are apt to tread on Suares, if they go on heedleſs, and without a diligent Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpection. There are Thouſands that lye in wait to prey upon the imbicillity of Young Men and Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men; who like <hi>Syrens,</hi> labour to Charm them with ſweet flattering Notes, on Ruinous Coaſts, that they may gain by the Shipwreck of their Good Names; and what the induſtry of Indulgent Parents has laid up for them in reſerve, or already beſtowed on them; nay even what has been acquired by their own induſtry, e'er the Seducers of their Tranquility, found in an unluckey Moment, inſinuating ways to work upon good nature; and this is done by ſuch ſtudied Tricks, Arts and Devices, to winde themſelves into the good liking, confidence and truſt of the Young<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger Sort; that Learning, Parts, and an indifferent Stock of Prudence are not very often a ſufficient Defence, againſt the invading Miſchief, that has of late ſpread like a Gangren; not to the undoing of a particular Perſon, but to the invitable Overthrow of many Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milies, which (had this dangerous Rock been avoid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, whereon their Fame and Fortunes are broken) might have been at this day proſperous and flouriſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing. But ſince paſt things cannot be recalled, let thoſe that lie open and lyable to the like danger and miſcarriages, take timely Warning and Advice, as a Sovereign Remedy againſt ſuch a ſweeping Contagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, which labours to become in a great meaſure E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pidemical, to the Juvenile Portion of Mankind; for let me tell you, when the ſcurvy Hour of ſo great a Misfortune has overtaken any of us, we may then grow angry with our ſelves, and would perhaps grow
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:35213:3"/>Wiſer, ſee our Folly, and in what we have been before ſhort-ſighted, and over-reached. Allowing then we could hinder or prevent it, if it were to be done a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain, though ſome indeed, too much relying on their own ſtrength, for want of ſound Advice, and a true Inſight of the matter, after ſuch Reſolves of taking good Heed to their Ways; have ſtumbled in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to a deeper Pit than before, as not Remembering, that we can no more have Wiſdom than Grace, when ever we think fit to call for it; there are Times and Periods fixed for both, and when they are too long neglected, the Puniſhment is, they are irrevocable, and nothing remains, but a uſeleſs Grief for the Fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly of having thrown them out of our power.</p>
               <p>It's a dangerous Step Youth make into the World, when they think they are capable of deal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing with it; for ſuch is the depravity of the Times, that even Virtue alone will not ſecure one, except it is attended with a great deal of Prudence, and both are but neceſſary for their Guard: Nor ought they to ſtir without them; for the Enemy is abroad, and they are ſure to be taken, if they are found ſtragling.</p>
               <p>Thus much by way of Introduction, and Precau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; my next Buſineſs is, to come cloſer or more Home to ſuch things as will be immediately neceſſary to be known by all, that would avoid being Impoſed on or ſlyly cheated of their Senſes, in too fondly be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieving the Inſinuating Flateries of ſuch as labour with both hands to pull down a ſpeedy Ruin on them.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:35213:4"/>
               <head>CHAP II.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>The Flattery and Inſinuations by <hi>Town-Shifts, Sharpers, Sharks,</hi> &amp;c. to work upon the Humours, Paſſions of the Mind, Inclinations, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> of the Younger, to bring about their pernicious Deſigns; with ſome Alluſions, and apt Stories, by way of Caution.</p>
               </argument>
               <p>THE Task I have undertaken is ſo difficult, and the Perſons I am about to deſcribe ſo many, their Ways, Practices and Vices ſo various, though they all concenter in one main Deſign to ruin Youth, that I cannot but fancy, my Young Reader upon firſt fight will conclude I have enterprized an Impoſſibi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity; or, that to be performed effectually by any ſingle Perſon, it may appear a <hi>Herculean.</hi> Labour; how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever, let none be ſo incredulous as to doubt, but when it is read over, it will anſwer, if ſeriouſly weighted and revolved in the Mind, the niceſt Expectation.</p>
               <p>In the firſt place then, it is the Care and Induſtry of ſuch as deſign to deceive and betray Youth, to find a way to ſlide unto their Acquaintance, and when that is a little ſetled, to inſinuate themſelves into their Affections, ſtudying the Bent and Paſſions of their Inclinations, which thoſe that are well ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed in the Art of deceiving, will ſhrewdly gueſs at, by the Complexion of Party: then they flatter them with all the Endearments of reſpect and cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dial Kindneſs, ſeeming afflicted when they are af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flicted, and to rejoyce when they have any tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ports of that Pleaſing Paſſion; ſetting a Gloſs even upon their Faults and Failings, wrong naming their
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:35213:4"/>Vices, and clouding them under the appearances of Virtue; calling Pride a Genteel Mien and gallantry of an Exalted Spirit; Prodigality the effect of a Generous Mind; deſires of Revenge, Courage and an uncontroulable Magnanimity; Drunnkenneſs Compla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cency, and an agreeable Companion; and for ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny others, they want not flattery to gild them o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, and make them look lovely in the conceit of Unthinking Youth who for the moſt part has an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bred Enemy to aid theſe Sycophants, <hi>viz.</hi> Self-flat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tery, a Thirſt of Praiſe, and deſire to be Eſteemed: and by theſe, and the like means, like ſubtil Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pents they wind themſelves into the Boſom, and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections of thoſe they intend to prey upon; and get ſuch Credit with the parties, that the good advice of real Friends is moſtly abortive, in labouring to open the Eyes of the Infatuated, that they may ſee, and purge out the ſpreading Bane, by timely Remi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies e'er it grows mortal. Flattery, as I ſaid, is their main Engin to make the firſt Breach, and make a way for them to enter. If theſe deceivers perceive a Perſon Cholerick, ſubject to Quarrel and Revenge, as naturally prompted to it by that fiery Humour pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dominating in the Conſtitution, when they hear him complain of wrongs or Injuries, though perhaps himſelf has been the Aggreſſor, they preſently ſtrike in to ſwell his Wrath, and cauſe the fluctuating Ocean of his Indignation to riſe, toſſing him with a Tempeſt of bitter Inuectives againſt thoſe that have put him out of Humour, magnifying the Truſt he has in them, to let them know his grievance; vowing with horrid imprecations to aſſiſt him at the hazard of their Lives in his juſt Revenge; but when they have born up his Courage, or rather Rage to a pitch, it there be any evident Danger in
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:35213:5"/>the Enterprize, then they ſhrink from him, leaving him in the Broil; which ſometimes coſts him his Life, or at leaſt much Trouble. Yet for this coward<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly forſaking, they have ſo many plauſible Excuſes, as Indiſpoſition, ſudden Lameneſs, ſeeing Bailiffs waiting to arreſt them, whoſe troubleſom preſence they were conſtrained to avoid; vowing not the fear of Sacrificing Life, ſhould other ways have hindred them in the Enterprize; and Expreſſing ſuch a world of Sorrow for their remiſsneſs to ſo dear a Friend; that after ſome Words paſſing, the Hal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cyon Sea appears again, and they ſail off ſmoothly on his Affections, as before: For theſe indeed are a Cowardly Generation, more for Bluſtring, Noiſe and Talk than Blows; and many a one, for relying on them to back him, has fallen into ſtrange and dangerous Misfortunes; for they are but Reeds, and whoever leans on them for Support, they break, and pierce his hand.</p>
               <p>If they croud by Inſinuation unto the good like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of a Perſon more moderate, and find him of a <hi>Sanguin</hi> Conſtitution, then their Proem is tuned to another ſtrain, they applaud his Temperateneſs, and flowneſs to Anger, as a premeditated and innate Prudence, flatter him with a Mitigation of the Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence, or at leaſt to take but a moderate Satisfaction; not to vex nor diſquiet his Spirits, but rather let the Injury dye in oblivion, than wreck it ſelf but in thoughts, to the hindrance of his Repoſe; or leave it to Heaven, which will not in due time fail to pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh the Injury ſo unjuſtly done him, without any colourable Cauſe; and this kind of Flattery, bear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing much upon his Inclination, makes him who is promptly good-natur'd, and inclinable to forgive, take all for Cordial Advice, and his well-timing Flatterers, for the deareſt of his Friends; ſo that af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:35213:5"/>this, and little more tryal, he thinks himſelf bleſſed, that as he foundly thinks them his Good An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels have luckily ſtumbled on him; ſo that from that time they Date their Advantage over him. The <hi>Phlegmatick</hi> Perſon theſe Tempters know to be fearful, and inclinable to avoid Danger, or under-take any Weighty Matters; his Fears magnifying every thing to him, and even at a diſtance ſhew them much frightfuller than they are; and with ſuch they ingratiate themſelves in another manner; labour to oblige him, and ingratiate themſelves, by ſtiling his Fear or Cowardiſe an averſion to Quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rels, that proceed, from Prudence and Caution; that nothing but raſh unadviſed Folly ruſhes Men upon Dangers that may be avoided; and that ſeldom ever hinders her Children from contending for Trifles; and well knowing no Man is pleaſed to be accounted a Coward, though he is ſo, they vindicate him in all Company where any Diſpute ariſes, though they Laugh in their Seeves at the ſame time: Inſtancing witty <hi>Horace,</hi> who once being in a Battel, and run<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning away when he ſaw the dreadful claſhing of Swords, and the mighty ſlaughter the waſtful Hand of War had made, being upbraided of Cowardize, his Anſwer was, that he thought it not fit that a Man of Sence ſhould ſtay to have his Brains beat out by illiterate Blockheads, that had none.</p>
               <p>By theſe and ſuch like Wiles, they work up and inſinuate themſelves into this Perſon; bind him to them by inſenſible Chains of Flattery, to live on his Fortunes, and make him ouly a return of Peſtiferous Air for Subſtantial Things; and like Horſe-leeches, drain even his vital Blood in the conſuming his Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance.</p>
               <p>Where they find <hi>Melancholy</hi> makes it's dull and lumpiſh abode, it for the moſt part excludes Joy
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:35213:6"/>and a livelyneſs of the Spirit; the Countenance ſhews this, and they ſoon take the hint to wind themſelves in the good Opinion of the Perſon; by inſinuating a deep Sorrow and much Reſervedneſs, when they ſee it ſeaſonable; here like the Devil trans<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed into an Angel of Light, they cover themſelves with a Veil of Hypecriſy, applying comfortable Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſions from Scripture; that he ſhould not afflict, or give himſelf up to Sorrow and Heavineſs, which border on the Land of Diſpair, and may in the end pluage him into that woful Gulf where ſo many have been loſt: Yet at the ſame time, to pleaſe him, ſtile his deiectedneſs a reſerved temper, and a ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſtering himſelf from the Vanities of the World: Inſtancing to him the Lives of the Philoſophers and others, whoſe Gravity gained them laſting Monu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of Renown. Sometimes when they perceive it may be more taking, they ſtile it a Contemplative Life, a Converſation with thoughts of the other world; and ſeem highly to approve it as the beſt and moſt agreeable with the Temper of the wiſeſt in all Ages, the very Pathway to the Stars, and conducing to a Virtuous State.</p>
               <p>Theſe are not the only Ways by which they, as it were wind themſelves inſenſibly into the Affections of Youth, when once they have found an opportuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of getting into their company, by pretending a Knowledge of their Relations, Admiring their Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe, Ingenuity, Provident Management of Affairs; or to do them ſome little Services; but they have many others, as aping all their Virtues and Vices, and ſhewing an agreeableneſs in all their Inclinati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, forcing a Laughter at every inſipid and ridicu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous Story they tell, commending their Wit in any Flothy Diſcourſe; labouring by theſe and ſuch like Devices, to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>iſe their Pride in conceit of themſelvess
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:35213:6"/>that being ſwelled with it, and blinded with ſelf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conceit, they may not diſcern the Snares their Flat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tery is laying to intrap them. So the Fox in the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, perceiving the Crow on a Tree with a choice Morſel in her Beak, and being deſirous to poſſeſs himſelf of it, perſwaded her that ſhe was the faireſt of all the winged ſtrain, that her Wings ghſtred with brightneſs and caſt a luſtre from their very night; That her Voice was more harmonious than Philomel's, and raviſhing than the dying Swan's; when the fooliſh Bird taken with his flattering Praiſe, thinking all true, began to flutter her Wings, and to try how well ſhe could tune her harſh and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant Note, opening her Bill, let the Prey fall to the Ground, which crafty Reynard ſnatching up, haſtily devoured, and upraided her with her Folly, and too much Credulity, whilſt ſhe vext at a loſs paſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covery.</p>
               <p>Thus the Deceivers practiſe on Youth, and leave them when they have got their Ends, to repent at leiſure; they take up their thoughts in engaging them in ſo many things, if once they find they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin to be Muſing, that they leave them paſt think<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing on any thing that tends to relieve them from the Misfortune he is ruſhing upon. The Flatterer breaks his own Reſt in ſuch a Caſe, to frame new Devices and Entertainments, to keep him or her he deſigns upon, from ſtarting, or falling off; and appears in as many ſhapes as <hi>Proteus,</hi> to make his Company and Converſation deſirable.</p>
               <p>So <hi>Alcibiades</hi> acted the part of an Orator and Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſopher among the <hi>Athenians;</hi> he put on an Auſtere and Grave Countenance among the <hi>Thracians,</hi> he acted the Gallant and Carouſed it ſtrenuouſly; among the <hi>Ionians,</hi> he gave himſelf up to all the ſoft Plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures and Delights that Effeminate Country had ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſtomed
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:35213:7"/>it ſelf to; among the <hi>Perſians,</hi> he imitated their Luxury, complied with their Haughtineſs and Pride, in ſumptuous Apparel: and by ſuch means wound himſelf into their Affections, the better cloſely to carry on his Deſigns.</p>
               <p>But why ſtay I ſo long on ſmall things, when more profound Myſteries require to be midwifed into the World? that innumerable Miſchiefs, long brooding in the Gloom, may be expoſed to the Noon-day Sun. I therefore now come to break the Cockatrices Egg, and ſhew the ugly Serpent too many have warmed in their Boſom, and by it unthinkingly undone themſelves.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. III.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>A lively Character of a Gentile <hi>Town-Shift,</hi> with the Stratagems, Policies and Devices he uſes, to get into the Acquaintance of Young <hi>Country-Gentlemen;</hi> and others; with the Tricks he plays, to Rook them of their Money: and in concluſion, to Marry them to Lewd Women of the <hi>Town;</hi> under pretence of their being Heireſſes, or mighty Fortunes.</p>
               </argument>
               <p>THE <hi>Country-Gentleman,</hi> or one ignorant of the Ways and Tricks of the <hi>Town,</hi> is to conſider, that he is to be always on his Guard; and that Miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>truſt and Diffidence are the beſt Sinews of his Policy: for if he be over-credulous, and eaſy to be trained into a belief of ſeeming Appearances, to believe Things ſubſtantial, when they are only Shadows; he lays himſelf open to many Inconveniencies and Misfortunes: for on this weak ſide he muſt expect Attacks, that will carry the Fort either by Parley or Storm.</p>
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:35213:7"/>
               <p>But before I come to diſcover how this is done, it will not be amiſs to give a brief Character of the moſt dangerous Enemy, that under a cloaked and diſſembled Friendſhip, will (if he meets him, or finds, for that he will certainly do, if he knows or hears of him, an opportunity to get into his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany, and ſcrape acquaintance with him) lay him on board; ſhewing firſt falſe Colours, to hale and allure him into his Power; and declares himſelf, or at leaſt by ſad Experience is found to be a Pirate, making his Fortunes by the Ruins of his Prize.</p>
               <p>He is by ſome called a <hi>Town-Gallant,</hi> but more vulgarly known by the Epithet of the <hi>Gentile Town-Shift,</hi> often ſhifting and changing his Cloathes and Lodging; for he deſires as little to be known, as inquired after. He has been well educated, having ſomething of the Education of a Gentleman, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the Fortune; his Father by his riotous way of living, having left him no other Portion than the wide World to live in: and he remembring ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing of his Gentility, cannot be forced, even by pinching Neceſſity, to undertake any induſtrious, lawful Employment; leſt he ſhould ſtain, as he pretends, the Reputation of his Family. He has been himſelf bubbled, and concludes it no Sin to ſet up, and practiſe it on others: and to perfect him ſo to do, and live on their Spoils, he makes it his Buſineſs to gain Experience; by Travelling abroad in the company of ſome young Gentlemen, who bear his Charges; that he may ſeaſon himſelf with a ſmattering of Forein Languages, learn the alamode Shrug-cringe, and ſome other Mimick Deportments. Being ſo qualified, and armed with a good Stock of Confidence, his Garb being modiſh and gentile; for without theſe, he could not ſo con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veniently thruſt himſelf into Company fit for his
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:35213:8"/>purpoſe. The next thing is to lay his Conſcience aſleep; and therefore among thoſe like himſelf, he profeſſeth himſelf in word and deed an abſolute Atheiſt, ſmiles at the mention of Hell-Torments<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> and is ready to burſt with Laughter, when he hears any diſcourſe of Spirits, and their apparitions; de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nying with horrid Oaths, any other Angels than thoſe in Peticoats, ſtaircaſed with Fringe or Lace, to lead his Fancy as high by gradation as Loves pretty Dimple, or ſip Ambroſial Nectar from the Ruby. Lip of the tempting Sex, and this he concludes his Paradiſe; ſuppoſing Hell to be no more than a Hot-houſe, to Flux for a Clap; denying there is an eſſential difference between Good and Evil: deems Conſcience only a thing fit for Women and Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, ſtiling the Devil the Parſon's Bugbear, and the civil Gentleman in black; aſcribing good Morals and honeſt Dealing to Simplicity, and a ſtupid Ignorance in the Facetious Humors and Ways of the <hi>Town.</hi> Yet, as I have in the former Chapter hinted, he can act variouſly, to comply with the different Humors of thoſe he deſigns to prey on.</p>
               <p>And having thus briefly given you his Character, I come now to his Practice; Diſſimulation, Flattery, Patience, feigned Humility, Affability, Civility, and Plauſibility, are the Weapons he charges with, as he ſees occaſion.</p>
               <p>He is acquainted much at Inns, and often rides ſome Miles out of Town, to view the Stage-Coaches as they come to <hi>London;</hi> and if he ſees any young Gentleman he can put-upon, he rides near, or within ſight of the Coach, 'till it comes to it, proper Stage; ſets up in the ſame Inn, where the Chamberlain, Tapſter and Hoſtler, and all the Dome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſticks give him great Reſpect, with worſhipful
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:35213:8"/>Titles; becauſe he is bountiful to them, for their particular Services, in learning of the Coach-man the Gentleman's Name, the Place from whence he came, that of his Birth, his Quality, and the Occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion that brought him to Town; but moſt of all the ſtrength of his Purſe; and what elſe can conve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niently be known. This done, he finds an oppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunity to inſinuate himſelf into his company, by doing him ſome little piece of Service; upon pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence of being alone, and a Stranger, deſirous of Company, and particularly of his; proteſting, after ſome ſmall introductory Diſcourſe of Complimenting and Cringing, that his Phyſiognomy takes him extreamly, that he ſees much Gallantry in it, manly and brave, frank and generous; proteſting he is wholly engaged to ſerve him; then binds it with an Oath, that if he had the Honour to be known to him, he is a Man ſincere, and an utter Enemy to Flattery; though at the ſame time all is notorious Flattery, that he may wind himſelf into his good Opinion, on purpoſe to deceive and betray him: and when he perceives he has wrought him ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing to his purpoſe, the better to confirm him in his feigned Sincerity, he changes the Diſcourſe after two or three Glaſſes have paſſed, and to wheedle an acquaintance with him, tho' he never ſet Eyes on him before: for fixing his Eyes upon him, and gazing ſtedfaſtly, as if ſome Apparition preſented it ſelf, he falls back in a ſtart; ſaying, Ha! who is this I ſee? O that I ſhould be thus long blinded! What my deareſt Friend, and I not know him all the while? When the Gentleman pauſes, and wonders at this; and can by no means call to mind he ever ſaw his Face before; he calls him by his Name, and tells the Place of his Birth or Abode, as he had learned it in the Inn before<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hand;
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:35213:9"/>crying, I now perceive the old Proverb is true, <hi>Out of Sight, out of Mind.</hi> But is it poſſible, ſix or ſeven Years ſhould blot me out of your Memory? It's ſtrange, that in ſo ſhort a time you ſhould forget one that profeſſes himſelf the greateſt Friend and Servant to your Family, of any Man living. Pardon me Sir, ſays the Gentleman, that I cannot ſo readily call you to mind, for I do not at preſent remember I ever ſaw you before. That's very ſtrange indeed, replyes he, there's ſcarce one of your Family that I do not know, as well as I know you: when I lived at <hi>D</hi> — there was no doing without me, I was always among them, I had the honour to ſee you there almoſt every day, Pray' how do you call the Place at <hi>D</hi> —, where they uſed to walk under cool refreſhing Shades in the Summer-Evenings? What, replyes the Gentle. man, the Grove? The ſame, ſays he, directly; there I paſſed many pleaſant Hours with delight, in you good company: — you don't remember this: Not I, I proteſt, ſays the Gentleman. Well, replys the <hi>Sharper,</hi> there are a hundred things a Man I ſee may forget, but no matter, let us em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brace, and renew our former Acquaintance. This makes the poor Gentleman wonder, and recollect himſelf all he can: when our <hi>Town-Shift</hi> perceiving him pauſing, and at a ſtand, as half-wrought into a belief of what he had ſaid, thus proceeds to give the finiſhing-ſtroak. Pary Sir, ſays he, tell me ſome News of your Family: — How does that Gentleman? — your — he that is ſuch at honeſt good Man. Who mean you, ſays the Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tleman, my Brother-in-Law the Juſtice on the Green? — The very ſame, ſays the other, by the ſame Token, if it be the ſame I mean, he Married your Siſter: he did ſo, replyes the Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man,
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:35213:9"/>why he is very well, and keeps up his old Jovial Humour: I am glad to hear it, ſays the other: and pray' how does the good Gentleman your Uncle, replies the Gentleman? I have no Uncle. — Here finding himſelf tripping, he recollects, and in a modeſt Tone ſays, Pardon me Sir, perhaps you had when I left the Country. — No, never, replies the Gentleman, only an Aunt. Alack alack! ſays he, that I ſhould ſo miſtake, it was directly ſhe I meant; if I miſtake not, ſhe was your Father's Siſter. She was ſo, reply'd the Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tleman, and I find you have ſome knowledge of my Relations, tho' I cannot well at preſent call you to mind. Having thus tickled the Tr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>t, and not willing to venture farther on this Subject, leſt he ſhould, ſtumble, and loſe his hold: the next thing is to fall to Drinking, or it may be a ſmall Collation is introduced; which our <hi>Town-Shift</hi> the better to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gratiate himſelf, will impoſe on him; ſuffering him at this time to pay nothing, though he be never ſo deſirous to do it: proteſting it is the Cuſtom of the Town, to welcom Friends at their firſt coming up; and that he knows better what belongs to Good Breeding, than not to obſerve it. So out comes a Gold-Watch, to ſee what Time it is; ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeded by a handful of Gold or silver, according as his Stock is: theſe are drawn on purpoſe to confirm his Credit, and gain him the greater Eſteem: whil'ſt the poor unthinking Gentleman little conſiders, that they are Spoils of others, and that himſelf e'er long muſt pay dear for his new Acquaintance.</p>
               <p>The next Intrigue is, to invite him if he is un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>provided, to his Lodging, 'till he can better furniſh himſelf; crying down the incommodiouſneſs of an Inn, occaſioned by Noiſe, ill Scents, and we know
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:35213:10"/>not who lying in their Beds, which may bring Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſes on a freſh Country-Gentieman, uſing to lye ſoft and delicate, and ſuddenly coming out of a refined Air into a groſſer: not forgetting to magnify the curious neatneſs of his own, where Attendance ſuiting his Quality ſhall be given, and in this matter becomes ſo importunate a Suitor, that no deni<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>l will ſerve his turn.</p>
               <p>The Reckoning being paid, and our Country-Gentleman mellowed with Drinking, a Coach is called, and away they rattle together: ſo that from this time he conclude: he his truſſed his Quarry. By the way he calls at a Muſick-Houſe, to diyert him with ſome of the fulſom Humour of the Town; and enters, from what he hath a Proſpect of there, ſome obſcene Conceits in his Head, the better to bring him to his Lure. If other Means fail, the next place is a Tavern; where out <hi>Town-Shift</hi> being well known, is received, and attended with Titles of Honour, and much ſeeming Reſpect, by the Vintner, his Wife, Daughter, and Drawers: and the rather, becauſe at his firſt approaching the Bar, and demanding whether My Lord, or Sir <hi>William</hi> Such a one had been there to aſk for him, he Tipt them the Wink or Sign, that he had brought a Bubble with him; which made them conclude, they were likely to reap a Share of the Profit he intended to make of him.</p>
               <p>A Bottle or two paſſing, and it growing late, they, take Coach again, and to our <hi>Shift</hi>'s Lodging, tho' perhaps but a few Doors diſtant; the Matron of the Houſe receives him with genteel Welcoms, and a profound Civility; the Servants imitate her in every thing, as knowing they ſhall be no loſers by it. And tho' our <hi>Shift</hi> before lay in a Garret to ſave Charges, now the beſt Chamber is made ready, and
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:35213:10"/>all things agreeable provided, and after ſome Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe, to Bed they go: but the Gentleman wrought to this pitch, tho' weary, muſt not ſleep, 'till by cunning Fetches and Wheedling, our <hi>Shift</hi> has got an Inſight into his Affairs; that not being ignorant of the depth of the Water he's Angling in, may the better know how to lay his Bait to take the more certainly, when the Gudgeon is leaſt apprehenſive of being entangled.</p>
               <p>Next morning, to keep up the Conceit of this Fatal Friendſhip, a Collation is prepared, and a She pretended Coſin comes, in very gawdy Tinſil Trap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pings, Modiſh, and appearingly very Rich; aſks for our <hi>Town-Shift,</hi> by the Title of Sir <hi>William,</hi> or Sir <hi>Thomas,</hi> deſiring of the Landlady to know, if he be yet ſtirring; if not, that ſhe would not diſturb his Worſhip: for ſhe is going to their Aunts, Madam ſuch a one, and will call again as ſhe returns. But being inform'd he is up, ſhe bawls to the Coach-Man to ſtay, ſo loud, that the young Gentleman above may hear her: and this is alſo a Watchword to her Bully, that has him in his clutches; who knowing her Voice, and having privately ſent for her to carry on the Intrigue, begins to proclaim her Quality before ſhe enters; and how lucky he is, that now he can oblige his deareſt Friend with the Cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſation of one of the fineſt and moſt accompliſhed Women the Town affords.</p>
               <p>By this time, ſoftly tripping up Stairs, ſhe enters, and pretends to Bluſh, that ſhe has intruded a Stranger: being there, making an Excuſe, with the Courteſy her <hi>French</hi> Dancing-Maſter taught her, and much feigned Modeſty; but her pretended Coſin interrupts her, ſaying, Madam, ſtand not upon Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remonies, this Gentleman is my good Friend, and you may be free; pray' how does the good Lady
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:35213:11"/>your Mother: to this ſhe returns a ſutable Anſwer: and then the Gentleman upon a Wink, and other ſignificant Motions of our <hi>Town-Shift,</hi> takes up the Glaſs, and preſents his Humble Service to this <hi>Town-Jilt,</hi> who drops a Courtlſy of another faſhion; re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiving it from him with a cold and diſſembled Coyneſs: proteſting, it is not her cuſtom to drink Wine in a Morning; but rather than prove trouble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſom, ſhe will pledge him: then ſhe ſips, as if ſhe were afraid to wet her Lips; and indeed ſhe is, becauſe they are Vermilion'd over, to give them a charming aſpectithen ſhrugs up her Shoulders, expoſes to view the Apples of her ſnowy Breaſts, then ſud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denly hides them, as if it had been done by chance, clapping her Hand before her Face, looking with half an Amorous Leer, whilſt her Eyes ſeem lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſhing, and by preſſing hard her Cheeks, ſhe raiſes a Bluſh on them. All this while our young Gentleman beholds with Admiration, and takes her to be the moſt accompliſhed Creature Fortune or Chance e'er caſt in his way; he intreats her to ſit, and participate of what the Table affords, or of any thing elſe that Money can command: but ſhe mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſtly refuſes it, and pretending a world of haſte, withdraws after a ſlight Compliment or two more; whil'ſt he much regrets the removal of ſo fair an Idea from his ſight. But the pretended Coſin ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſes it, urging he knows her Buſineſs; and that if ſhe diſpatch it not, and return in time, ſhe will incur the diſpleaſure of her Mother; on which, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides her preſent Fortune that none can hinder her of, depends ſome Thouſands of Pounds, which however ſhe will be ſure of at her Death. If he be an Unmarried Man, this takes to Admiration, and he is Smitten, as we call it, at the firſt Touch. A Beauty and a Fortune ſtrangely charm him, and he
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:35213:11"/>hugs himſelf in Raptures, to conceit he hath ſuch a Friend to facilitate his Addreſſes, to open the way for his Courtſhip, and render it eaſy.</p>
               <p>Our <hi>Shifter</hi> perceiving this Bait hath taken to his wiſh, ſoon dives into the Affairs that brought him to Town; what Eſtate he hath, if his Friends be dead, or what he expects, if they be living; and by a kind of an imperceptible inſinuating, wheedles things out of him in ambiguous terms, 'till he underſtands his Humours and Affairs, as well, or better than himſelf.</p>
               <p>And now is the time to ſtart his Game, and run it down with all convenient ſpeed, leſt ſome unlucky Accident ſhould make him loſe it: as a Diſcovery, the Gentleman's being ſuddenly ſent for Home, Sick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, or the like. He pretends, and deſires earneſtly, to aſſiſt him in his Affairs, if they urgently preſs it, that Morning; if not, to ſhew him the Curioſities of the Court or City.</p>
               <p>But certainly he will be ſure to inveigle him to Dine at an Ordinary; or ſuch a place, where he hath, or will by that time ſend to ſome of his Accomplices to meet him; to whom he always gives Noble or Worſhipful Titles, the better to carry on the Intrigue without ſuſpicion: and they return his Civility with profound Reſpect, and bridle in their accuſtomed Oaths, that they may not be ſuſpected to be what they are; and turn their Diſcourſe on State-Affairs, or what Sport they had in Hawking, Hunting, and other Genteel Recreations; when they went to Viſit ſuch a Lord or Knight at his Country-Seat. Then every one Salutes the Stranger, and Welcomes him to Town.</p>
               <p>Dinner being ended, they Drink about Juſtily, impoſing on our Country-Gentleman ſo many Healths, 'till they perceive his Brains begin to crow, then to
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:35213:12"/>paſs away the Tedious Time, as they term it, the Dice are called for; not by his pretended Friend, but by the other Confederates: for he ſeems to oppoſe it, that he may be thought to have no Hand in the Plot.</p>
               <p>When the upſhot comes, and ſo much Money is ſeemingly loſt and won between them, at length our <hi>Town-Shift</hi> ſets in, and Wins prodigiouſly, which encourages the Country-Gentleman to Bett, who is ſuffered likewiſe to Win; which, with ſome other Incitements, puts him on to Play himſelf; and then, as out of courteſy, his pretended Friend gives him his place, ſome ſmall matter he wins; but prompted to Set high, the Dice turn upon him; for they Top and Palm, throwing Dice themſelves that will run but to the deſired Chances; and by the Art of <hi>H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>cus-Pocus</hi> and a cleanly Conveyance, ſo neatly recover them, that a curious Eye can ſcarcely diſcern it: ſo that perhaps in a little time the Money he had about him fails, and is ſlipped out of his into their Pockets. Then his Friend <hi>Shift</hi> ſeems to be diſpleaſed that he brought him thither, proteſting he was againſt Playing, and ſorry for his croſs luck; yet bids him not be dejected, though Fortune proves now a Jilt, another time ſhe may favour him, to recover all with a large addition to boot. This, if he has any Bills to receive Money in Town, brings them out; and their ſeeming un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>willingneſs to engage any farther, makes him more eager to go on. His Friend then Betts on his ſide, and he hath ſome little Luck again, but quickly the Tide turns; for they are for ſtriking whil'ſt the Iron is hot, and all is daſht again. This vexes him ſo, that off comes the Diamond-Ring, and out comes the Watch; but here his Friend ſtops him, for he has a mind theſe ſhould be beſtowed elſewhere:
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:35213:12"/>and then the others knowing the meaning of it, ſneak out one by one, pay at the Bar, and rub-off, leaving him and Mr. <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> together; the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doles the Misfortune of our Country-Gentleman, and as a Sugar-Plum, offer <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> Money, on his Bond, or not; to keep up his Character <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> he can be ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plied. This, and two or three briſk Glaſſes, put him out of his dumps; and a Scrivener being ſent for, 'tis accepted with thankfulneſs, on the Terms propounded: which Civility, and others formerly received, obliges him to Pay the Shot for them both, and be liberal to the Servants.</p>
               <p>Hereupon a Coach is called, and away to Airing they go to St. <hi>James</hi>'s, or <hi>Hide-Park,</hi> if ſeaſonable; if not, to the <hi>Tennis-Court,</hi> or to take a view of the Tombs at <hi>Weſtminſter:</hi> but where-ever it is, as the Plot was laid in the Morning, they meet the She-Coſin with her Footman at her tail; this ſeems to the Gentleman, as by wonderful accident; and ſo ſhe proteſts, the better to confirm him in his Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion of her little deſire to go, or be ſeen abroad.</p>
               <p>The renovation of this charming Sight joſtles all thoughts of his Loſſes out of his Head, and after a turn or two, where muſt they go but to the Play-Houſe. Our <hi>Town-Shift</hi> ſtarts this, and Madamoi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelle with much ſeeming Modeſty declines it; urging, ſhe cannot ſpare Time; or that the Age is ſo cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſorious and ſcandalous, that it is not a Place conve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nient for her to be ſeen in.</p>
               <p>Her coldneſs maks the young Gentleman importu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate, and our <hi>Town-Shift</hi> backs him in it, joining his Perſwaſion; ſo that at length it is agreed on, and away they are jolted together.</p>
               <p>The Gentleman, who never ſaw ſuch fine things before, is mightily taken, and vows, the Pleaſures of the Town as far exceed thoſe of the Country,
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:35213:13"/>as he fancies <hi>Mahomet</hi>'s Paradiſe exceeds the Deſarts of <hi>Arabia.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Play ended, they are obliged to ſee her home to her Apartment; and then, as a lucky hit would have it, the Lady-Mother talked on before, (there being no ſuch living Creature) is feigned to be at ſuch a Ladies Labour, or gone to ſee ſome ſick Counteſs.</p>
               <p>So that here the Eatertainment interrupted, is Splendid at the Coſt of our young Gentleman; who in Generoſity, having at ſuch Charge learned thus much of Town-Breeding, muſt Treat the Lady, in recompence of the Favour her Company hath (in complaiſance to his Requeſts) obliged him with.</p>
               <p>Her Acceptance emboldens him to talk Amo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rouſly, but ſhe ſeems not to underſtand him, and inſtead of returning his Glances, fixes her Eyes on his Diamond-Ring, proceeding to praiſe the beauty and ſplendor of it; ſaying, ſhe once had juſt ſuch another, preſented her by a Perſon of Honour, but hath loſt it; and to this day dares not let her Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther know ſo much. You told me Coſin, continues ſhe, directing her Diſcourſe to our <hi>Town-Shift,</hi> that you would ſpeak to the Jeweller, that made it for the Lady who preſented it me, for ſuch another; as for the Price, I will not ſtand with him. Truly Coſin, replied he, I forgot to tell you, I was with the Man I thought had made it, but it proves a Miſtake, he did not, nor can he inform me who did. I am ſorry for that, ſays ſhe, but I fancy this Gentleman's is extream like it; yet Modeſty for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bids me to be ſo rude, as to deſire a Stranger to truſt me with ſuch a value, for a Pattern.</p>
               <p>Our Gentleman, who all this while hath liſtned to this charming <hi>Syren,</hi> like a Nightingal to a Flajolet, mightily taken with her Carriage, thinks now he
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:35213:13"/>hath an Opportunity ſubſtantially to oblige ſo ſweet a Creature, as he ſuppoſes her; and if he be not Married, makes one great Step to gain her, and her prodigious Fortunes in the Clouds; prompted by Mr. <hi>Shift</hi> with Nods and Winks, makes no ſcruple, not to lend it her, but preſents it as his Act and Deed; which ſhe ſeems in Modeſty to refuſe, 'till he in a manner is compelled to force that upon her, which ſhe ſo earneſtly deſires; and muſt, as our <hi>Shift</hi> whiſpers in his Ear, take it as a Favour that ſhe will accept it.</p>
               <p>This makes her look with more gracious Eyes upon him; ſo that having found the Fruits of the firſt Preſent, his Gold-Watch goes next; and he plyes her with many others, to ſpeak more power<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully for him than his Rhetorick can do.</p>
               <p>To be brief, he ſo prevails at laſt, that ſhe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſents he ſhall Steal her, but not 'till a good Settle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment is made. The Management of the Buſineſs is left to our <hi>Town-Shift,</hi> who is gratified with Gold, fringed Gloves, and other coſtly things, on the Wedding-Day; the Marriage being celebrated very privately.</p>
               <p>This done, he hath ſcarce time to Embrace his charming Bride, whom he finds the firſt Night but a crackt Bargain, if he ſcape a Clap; ere her Tay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lor, Tally-man, Landlady, Silk-man, Lace-man, Draper, Shooe-maker, Tire-woman, and a Shoal more ſurround him at his ſetting forth from his Chamber, with their Bills, and clamour for the Money his Bride owes them. And this he muſt take as a Civility; for ſometimes two or three couple of Harpy-Catchpoles ſeize him at the bot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tom of the Stairs.</p>
               <p>In fine, his pretended Friend Mr. <hi>Shift</hi> hath now plaid his Prank, and is withdrawn to ſhare the Booty
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:35213:14"/>with the Gameſters. And he hears no more of him but for the Money he lent him. Upon Enquiry, hi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Spouſe proves no better nor no worſe than a Second-rate Strumpet, who like a Squirrel hath learned the Trick of covering her whole Body with her Tail; and has no more than her Brain to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trive Cheats, and carry on Intriguing-Wickedneſs for her Dowry.</p>
               <p>Her feigned Modeſty now is vaniſhed, and if he dares upbraid her with the Misfortune that hath befallen him, ſhe twits him with his Folly and Ignorance in the Ways of the Town, roars, ſlings and rants like any Bedlam; and Swears now ſhe is Wife, ſhe will make him know his Driver; a Coach ſhe will have, and Freedom at all times.</p>
               <p>Coſin <hi>Shift</hi> is ſtill her Gallant, and goes Snips with her in all ſhe can rook her deceived Huſband of; who to keep her quiet, and the Misfortune as huſh as may be among his Relations in the Country; to ſupply her Luſt, Luxury, Pride, and other Expen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſives, firſt Mortgages, then Sells outright, after runs in Debt; and if his Heart be ſo ſtrong as not quickly to break with theſe Afflictions, he may linger out ſome Years in the <hi>Kings-Bench</hi> or <hi>Fleet,</hi> or flying a Gaol, meet with as bad Misfortunes in a Forein Land. As for his Wife, ſhe is ſtill in her Element, nay hath bettered his Fortunes by a Reſerve; and when grown Old, ſhe knows the worſt of it; if Poverty compels her, 'tis but to turn Bawd or Procurer.</p>
               <p>As for her Original, ſhe was the Cub of a Bumpkin, licked into ſhape, ſent up to <hi>London</hi> in a Green Waſtcoat and Red Peticoat, to be thrown on the Care of Fortune; from a Cloſeſtoole-Emptier, ſhe riſes to be a Cook-Maid, from thence, crept up Stairs to manage the Bedding and Carpets; in which
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:35213:14"/>Station growing ſpruce, and Nature having endued her with a tolerable Face, and a large Stock of Confidence ſhe was Boarded a-ſtern by the young 'Squire her Maſter's Son; when complaining to him that her Belly wambled, he put her off with a piece of Money: upon which, ſhe took Sanctuary under the Protection of an old Bawdy Midwife, who having delivered her, and dropt the Child as a Pariſh-Charge, adviſed her to turn Town-Woman, or a Woman of the Town; and taught her how to practiſe, going Snips with her for Counſel. But often meeting with Affronts, to ſkreen her againſt them, ſhe choſe our <hi>Town-Shift</hi> for her Bully; who brought her Cuſtomers, and went ſhare in the Profit.</p>
               <p>I might enlarge much more on this, but having many things to treat of before I finiſh this ſmall Book; I muſt intreat the Reader not to expect too large a Birth in the beginning; leſt the ſubſequent Relations prove but Pigmeys, for want of room, to grow to their deſired Stature.</p>
               <p>I have mentioned already indeed ſomething of <hi>Gaming,</hi> and it might reaſonably have been ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected I ſhould have diſcovered the Tricks and Cheats uſed in it by <hi>Shifts, Sharpers, Bulleys, Beaux,</hi> &amp;c. But then I muſt be obliged to repeat them ſo often, that they will appear Tautology: and therefore to avoid it, and not allow for more room than I can expect; I ſhall briefly diſcover, and lay them down, for the advantage of the Reader, by themſelves, when I come to a Concluſion.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="chapter">
               <pb n="26" facs="tcp:35213:15"/>
               <head>CHAP. IV.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>A <hi>Town-Shark,</hi> his lively Character. How he falls into the Acquaintance of Young <hi>Shopkeepers,</hi> by what Artifices he works his own Advantage, to bring them to Ruin. As alſo their Female Relations; and how in their Extremity, he practiſes greater Villanies againſt them: and other things, well worth noting.</p>
               </argument>
               <p>IN this Chapter, Young Men that by the help of Friends, or their own Induſtry, Set up, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin to make a Figure in the World, my Precautions are directed to you. For beſides Beaus and Fops, that will be apt to Wheedle you abroad, to make you neglect your Buſineſs, loyter away your Time, ſpend your Money, and endanger your Credit and Reputation.</p>
               <p>There lurks behind the Curtain a more peſtilent Enemy to your Fortunes, who makes it his whole Study and Buſineſs to nip them in their growth. Nor ought the Larks to cour, and be more afraid of the Hobby, who makes it his work to prey upon them, than Young Men adventuring on the Stage of Worldly Affairs, ought to conſider how they may ſhun meeting with this <hi>Hyena</hi> in Human ſhape. And that he may be the better known, and avoided, I ſhall firſt briefly deſcribe him, and ſo proceed to his Practices.</p>
               <p>He goes under many Denominations, which I ſhall not trouble my ſelf to enumerate, but trace him in the vulgarly known Epithet of a <hi>Town-Shark.</hi> He boaſts himſelf of his Parentage, and what a great Eſtate they had, but were Ruined for their Loyal Adherence to the Royal Family, in the late
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:35213:15"/>Civil War: though the truth is, like a <hi>Chedder</hi>-Cheeſe, the whole Milk of the Pariſh went towards making, or rather educating him. For his tender Mother, weary of a Burden ſhe knew not where to find a Father for, dropt, and left him as a Pariſh-Charge.</p>
               <p>However, growing up, the Charity of the Church-Wardens and Overſeers enabled him with a Smat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tering of Freeſchool-Learning: but his early Rogueries making the Maſter weary of him, he is turned out before he could term himſelf a Proficient in it, and threatned with the dreadful Drudgery of keeping Sheep, or feeding Swine; the Lazineſs of his Parentage being inherent, and cauſing in him an averſion to any thing that look'd like Labour; he to the Satisfaction of his Benefactors, gave them the ſlip, and trudges on bare Ten-toes, as the old Say<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing is, to <hi>London,</hi> the common Receptacle or Ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dezvous of Vagrants; where rambling about the other end of the Town, pennileſs, and almoſt ſtarved; his kind Stars at length favour him ſo far, that he gets a Lodging in a Gentleman's Stable, and is entertained by a lazy Coachman to rub down and feed his Horſes. From thence he riſes, to run of Errands for the Maid-Servants; who commending him for his Induſtry to their Maſter, time offering a vacancy, he is preferred to the dignity of a Foot-Man.</p>
               <p>And here he practiſeth to ſet up for himſelf, by learning to underſtand a Dey well, by often Playing with his Livery-Companions, Laced-Coat-Gameſters: nay even his nightly Dreams are tending to it, <hi>viz. Come at Seven,</hi> is often heard in his Sleep; and his Morning-ſtudy is, what Chance of the Dey is ſooneſt thrown, in topping, ſlurring, palming, napping, and how to fix a Dey for any purpoſe.</p>
               <pb n="28" facs="tcp:35213:16"/>
               <p>The next advance he makes, is to play on the Flajolet, Flute, Hautboy, or Violin; and for his Teaching, his Maſter's Bottles of Wine, Ale, Cyder, or Legs of Capons, moſtly pay, as he can filch them. And if he has any tolerable Voice, he learns to Sing ſomething tuneable, by imitating in the Upper Gallery at the Play-Houſe.</p>
               <p>Theſe Accompliſhments make the Cook-Maid fall in Love with him, and over-enamoured with his queint Diſcourſe, Shape and Features, truſts him before-hand with her Secrets, communicating ſo long, 'till her Belly begins to wamble; he all this while promiſing her Marriage, not ſcrupling to bind it with Oaths and Imprecations: ſo that the ſilly good-natured Wench believing all he ſays to be Goſpel, crams into his Hand the Money ſhe hath laid up, ſaved out of her Wages and Veils, to buy him a new Suit of Cloaths, a Wedding-Ring, and other Furniture; for the Day is appointed: with this making up his Pack, he rubs off, leaving her in Cares and Tears, to bewail her fond Eaſineſs and Credulity.</p>
               <p>The firſt thing after this is, like a Snake, to caſt his Skin of a Livery, and to put himſelf with his own, and poor Greaſy-buttocks Money, into a Gentile Sute; diſguiſing himſelf with a long Wig, and clapping on a faſhionable Sword. And ſo being a little tutored, and better grounded by ſome ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoned Sticks, into whoſe company he thruſts him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, or is introduced, he ſets up for a Proficient in this Deſtructive Calling. And now as to his Practice.</p>
               <p>O' Nights he is moſtly waking, to ſtudy Devices, that he may put them in practice in the Day; and get<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting up in the Morning, traces the Streets more than a Penny-Poſt-Letter-Carrier, caſting his Eyes on
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:35213:16"/>Both ſides the way, to ſpy and mark out his Game. Beſide, he hath intelligencers abroad, who give him notice what Young Men are newly Set up, and what they ſuppoſe their Stocks and other Fortunes to be: and when he hath pitched upon any one that he may gather from his Diſeourſe, what Temper he is of, ſeeing him alone, he ſteps in, and with a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaiſant Demeanour, intreats to borrow a Pen and Ink to write a few words; and then generouſly he draws a Bill for a good Summ, on ſome unknown Perſon: then leaving it careleſly, that the young Man may caſt his Eye on it, deſires his Sand-Box, which whil'ſt he is reaching, he begins to him a Line or two of ſome Play-Song: then preſently leaving off, as if he had done amiſs, in forgetting the place where he was; I beg your Pardon, Sir, ſay<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> he, for my rudeneſs, Pray' how goes Trade with you in the City? And when Anſwer is made, But ſo ſo, or, Indifferent; he begins to inveigh againſt ſome that he pretends are no Well-willers to the City, and Obſtructers of it, hoping to ſee better Days.</p>
               <p>And to prolong the Diſcourſe, the better to feel his Pulſe, if any thing of little Price be ſold in the Shop, he will lay out a ſmall trifling matter; the better to ingratiate himſelf, when he makes the ſecond Attack.</p>
               <p>And ſo at this time, with much Civility he takes his leave. And if he finds the Shopkeeper of an eaſy temper, from this Interview he Regiſters him in his Pocket-Book, amongſt his Culleys he intends to Bite. For thought he will not be ſo raſh the firſt time, as to aſk him his Name, leſt it may create ſome ſuſpicion of his Deſign.</p>
               <p>Knowing the Sign and Trade, he fails not to ſend another to inquire it in the Neighbourhood, that he
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:35213:17"/>may have it ready at his Tongues-end the next Attack he makes; and in the mean while, a Flute, or ſome ſuch Inſtrument is by his order left for him, by a Boy in a Green Apron, purpoſely dreſt up and ſent. And if at firſt the young Shopkeeper ſcruple to take it in, as proteſting he knows no ſuch Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man by Name, and believes he is miſtaken in the Houſe; the arch Knave has it at his fingers ends, by the ſame Token he was there ſuch a Day, and bought ſuch Things: then he is remembred, and it is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived. About an Hour or two after, he comes ratling in a Coach, the better to credit him. If he ſees the young Man buſy, or engaged in his Shop with Company, he paſſes by, and takes him in his return. If not, he puts out his Head and poudered Wig, bawling to the Coachman to ſtop: and boldly going in, and with a Modiſh Cringe and Air, aſks if he has not been troubleſom to him, in taking the boldneſs to order ſomething to be left for him; which he had not attempted, had it been finiſhed when he called at the Shop where he bought it, and this Place lying more directly in his way.</p>
               <p>The young Man hearing him make ſuch a Scruple for a Trifle, as he ſuppoſes, not perceiving the Snake in the Graſs, tells him he is welcom now, and at any time, to ſend or cauſe to be left any thing at his Shop, and it ſhall be laid up ſafely for him.</p>
               <p>Why, ſays he, living at t'other end of the Town, I may with your good leave, make bold now and then to trouble you. But pray' Sir, continues he, for this Kindneſs, and to confirm our better Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaintance; which if it lies in my power, ſhall be to your Advantage; Suffer me to preſent you with a Glaſs of Wine.</p>
               <p>The young Man perhaps at firſt ſeems coy, or pretends that he has ſome that he inſtantly expects,
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:35213:17"/>about Buſineſs. But he preſſes it with ſuch a Facetious Air, Mein, and ſeeming Generoſity, that he verily believes him to be of Quality: and that in doing it, he may both oblige a Gentleman, and ſuch a one as he may probably expect to be a Cuſtomer to him; or at leaſt engage others of his Acquaintance to advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage him that way.</p>
               <p>Then if there be no Apprentice, or he be out of the way, the Maid, Siſter, or ſome other is called down, to look to the Shop, 'till he ſteps a little way with the Gentleman. When entring the Tavern, and a Room being ſhewn, there is great ſtraining in Courteſy, who ſhall ſpeak for the Wine; that it may be known what ſort beſt gratifies the Palate. And ſeeing our Shopkeeper, who expects to be Treated, is ſo mannerly that he will not look a Gift-Horſe in the Mouth; his ſuppoſed Gentleman, that he may be ſure to hit right, calls for one Pint of White, and another of Red, with <hi>French</hi> Rowls. and after a chirping Cup, he pulls out his Flute, as he fays, to try it; and playing a Tune or two, directly fixes his Eye on our Youngſter's Face, to obſerve how the Paſſions agitate the Mind: From whence he gathers, whether he is delighted witls Harmony, or not; if he find he is, he frames a Diſcourſe of the Rarity of Muſick in other Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries, where he hath travelled; and that he will, in reſpect to his good Company ſo generouſly af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forded him, ſing him a Song he learnt of a <hi>Venetian</hi> Lady; and then confident he underſtands not <hi>Ita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lian,</hi> tunes his Voice to a certain Gibberiſh, which ſounds melodious enough to an unintelligent Ear, and extorts Applauſe from the Auditor.</p>
               <p>And thus in a little time, other diſcourſe paſſing about, they become as intimately acquainted, as if they had Sucked one Nurſe.</p>
               <pb n="32" facs="tcp:35213:18"/>
               <p>He ſtays not long at this time, but calling for the Reckoning, genteely Payes it; thought the other preſſes at leaſt to be his Share, in Complaiſance. This makes our Shopkeeper cudgel his Brains, in ſtudying as he goes to ſee him take Coach, how he may retaliate the Kindneſs of ſo ſweet a Gentleman, and can think of none, but the old way, of Sir, Will you pleaſe when you come this way, or to any place near my Houſe, to come and Dine with me; I'll promiſe you ſhall be heartily welcom to ſuch as you find; and if I certainly knew the time, I would pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vide ſomething better than ordinary.</p>
               <p>To this he makes ſeemingly modeſt Excuſes, as nnwilling to trouble him, 'till it is in his power to oblige him in ſomething that may deſerve it: which cauſes the other to preſs it the more, 'till he promiſe at one time or other to wait on him: but withal, charges him that he get nothing extraordinary when he comes, for he is not over-curious in his Diet: and vows, if he does, it will bar him from treſpaſſing for the future. And thus, with ſome Ceremony, they part.</p>
               <p>The Ice being now thorowly broken, he does indeed muſter up ſome of his Raggamuffin-Acquaintance, that recommended in his Name, (for he the laft Meeting left it with him) prove now and then Retale-Cuſtomers; that gaining a good Opinion for their ready Money, by degrees they may in the cloſe come into Credit for a full Sweep by Wholeſale: But theſe are moſtly Women, for there are many of his Intriguing-Companions he dare not truſt; leſt being more cunning at Intrigue, they ſhould ſtrike-in and wipe his Noſe: ſome few indeed he muſt, to carry on the Deſign.</p>
               <p>And thus having laid a Foundation of Acquain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance on the Sand, for our young Shopkeeper; and
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:35213:18"/>on a Rock for his own Advantage; he fails not to come about Dinner-time, that being introduced as a Familiar, he may the better diſcover the Houſe, ſee how it is furniſhed; and from thence take his Meaſures, when he comes upon the Borrowing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>account. For many times aſking for a Summ too high, and above the Perſon's ability that is required to lend it, daſher all; nay perhaps there may be a Siſter or Coſin, belonging to the Houſe, whoſe Portions are at their diſpoſal: and then if he finds them any thing eaſy to ſwallow his deceitful Baits, he concludes his Advantage double. After Dinner he will ſend for a Bottle or two, if his Stock will bear it; and then falls to talking, what a fine <hi>Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gedy</hi> or <hi>Comedy</hi> is to be Acted in the Evening, what curious Scenes or Singing they afford, for the Diver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſement of the Spectators and Auditors. By theſe and ſuch-like Diſcourſes, he finds our Young Man's Inclinations; and if he can, he will fix a Play upon him, to draw him farther from home, that he may be out of Call, and more in his power to practiſe on: for this is one he means to wean by degrees from his Shop, and when he is given to ramble, he is ſure to have him at his Beck.</p>
               <p>The Play ended, after long ſitting with dry Lips, they muſt take a Glaſs at the Tavern, and it muſt be where Mr. <hi>Sherk</hi> is intimately acquainted; where the Reſpect given him, in Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pectation of Gain, far ſurmounts his Quality, thought it adds to the Eſteem already conceived-of him by our Shopkeeper here. As by accident, he purpoſely ſtumbles on one or two of his Companions, and they muſt be of the Company, placed at a di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance one from another; and a Glaſs for two turned off, he deſires them to take farther acquain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance with this Gentleman his Friend, who is newly
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:35213:19"/>ſet up of ſuch a Trade, and if they can, aſſiſt a Young Man in his Way; he lays his Obligation on them to do it for his ſake; vowing he is the moſt obliging, civil Gentleman he ever converſed withal; and though but of late acquaintance, he finds that which obliges him to rank him amongſt the beſt of his Friends. And goes on farther to praiſe his Induſtry, Frugality, Good Parts, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> 'till the Young Man, though in wardly puffed up with his own Praiſe, from the Mouth of a flattering Varlet, modeſtly before Company thinks himſelf obliged to deſire him to deſiſt; excuſing ſo elaborate an <hi>Encomium,</hi> as not due to him; but more worthy to be placed ſomewhere elſe; ſalute him, and his Health goes about.</p>
               <p>Thus having ſwelled him like a Bladder, the next work is to give him Vent; upon a Signal of ſo many Knocks or Rings, to call up the Drawer, a Perſon purpoſely planted below takes the Hint, and the Wine carried up, in comes he with a Cloak down to his heels, making his Obeyſance to the Company, leaning one Hand at the lower end of the Table, and aſks for a ſtrange Name. In the mean while, he lets go a little Boy he brought concealed under his Cloak, trained up in the dextrous Art of Pick-pocketing from his Infancy. This young Knave crawls to our Citizen unſeen, the Table ſheltering him, and by a cleanly Conveyance bites him of his Watch and Money; then returns to his guardian, and is carried out undiſcovered, the ſame way he was brought in; our Shopkeeper, who fits at a diſtance from any body, not dreaming of any ſuch thing.</p>
               <p>After they have gazed upon one another, and aſked if any of them know the Man, and all of them affirming No; one whiſpers to the reſt, ſo loud
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:35213:19"/>that our Shop-keeper may hear him, he believes he is a Setter to the Vintner, whoſe head you broke for making you pay your Reckoning twice; for I heard him ſwear he would trounce you for it, and has been enquiring of moſt of your Friends, what Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vern you now uſe. At this the huffs, and ſeems not to value him; however, the Work being done for this time, it gives ſome colour for haſte to diſcharge the Reckoning, and one without more words, ſtepping down to the Bar, the Drawer comes up with Ye'r kindly welcome, Gentlemen, all's paid, and your Friend ſtays below, deſiring you would be pleaſed to walk down, which they haſtily do, and our Shop-keeper follows them with emptyed Pockets, admiring the Generoſity of his new Acquaintance, fondly conceiting a few more of theſe, would make him a Made Man for ever, if they help him to Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtom as they promiſe.</p>
               <p>He no ſooner parts with them at the Tavern-door, but one altogether a Stanger to him, acts the Drun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken Man, and joſtles him ſo, that ſomething of a Croud gets about them, but immediately diſſipates, and away he goes home: This is to colour the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, that he ſhould verily believe his Pocket was pick'd in the Street: For after he came out of the Play-Houſe he knew he had his Watch and Money, and in the Tavern, if he ſhould be ſo ungentile to ſuſpect any of the Company, which ſat at diſtance from him, to do it, as he thinks to himſelf, his own Reaſon, convinces him it could not be done; he not ſitting near any one by a Yard at leaſt; for ſo they placed themſelves on purpoſe, little dreaming of <hi>jack-in-a-Box:</hi> However he is ſomewhat dumpiſh at his loſs, and when his ſuppoſed Friend makes him the next Viſit, he tells him of it, who ſeems mighti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly concerned at ſuch a croſs Accident; and the more,
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:35213:20"/>becauſe he occaſioned his going abroad, Vowing to make him an equivalent; and ſoon confirms his belief of his Pocket being picked after they parted: For as for the Company you were in, I will engage my Life for their Integrity, they are Men of Eſtates, and great Worth; and as for the Perſon who came in with a frivolous pretence, the whole length of the Table was between you and him.</p>
               <p>This Diſcourſe palliates the Matter, and he con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cludes this loſs, frequent to others, might have hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pened if he had never gone to the Play-Houſe; my Money was not very much, ſays he, and as for a Watch, I have a Watch-maker owes me Money, which I believe I ſhall not get, unleſs I hedge it in by taking a Watch for it; and ſo that Flaw will be Sodered again.</p>
               <p>However; to drive the Thoughts of this loſs be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond returning again, to make him Melancholy, he begins to diſcourſe of Poetry, and repeats ſome Verſes, he has got by heart out of Plays, and if theſe affect him, out comes a Lampoon, he pretends to have made on a Court-lady, and when he has read it, and ſolved the <hi>AEnigmas,</hi> or what is obſcure in the Hints, he deſires him as a choice Friend, to take a Copy of it, which Favour he will allow to no other; And this is to try, if he be Poetically in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clined; as being aſſured, that Poetry behind a Counter, is a certain Mine to blow up Shoop-keep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing: For if a Trades-man get the knack of courting the Muſes, thoſe jilting jades lead him ſuch a Dance that he ſoon loſes himſelf; for being proud of his paltry Rhymes, he will ſeek Company, and at any rate ſeek to Herd amongſt a parcel of Fops and Buf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foons that call themſelves Wits, and would be ſo ſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led by others. Therefore as a ſpecial Note by the way, let all Young-men beware of this Folly, or ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:35213:20"/>Frenzy, that are fixed in any Trade or Calling.</p>
               <p>But to return now, if he be a ſingle Man, he be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gins to tickle him with a proſpect, he has of a fair Fortune for him; if married, he Plows with his Hel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer if it be poſſible; and it ſhall be hard if he winds not himſelf in with his Female, and by theſe Ways and Devices, gaining as it were an abſolute power o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver the Young-man, he pretends pulling out ſeveral Bills written by himſelf, though drawn upon Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chants or Rich Bankers, that he thinks the World declines apace, for he never met with ſuch Diſap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointments in his Life; theſe Bills, ſays he, as you may ſee, are due long ſince, and having layed out ſo much money in a Purchaſe, not in the leaſt doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing I ſhould receive this money, it has brought me ſomething to a ſtrait, that I proteſt I muſt be enfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced to treſpaſs upon ſome Friend or other, for a little time. Thus he wheedles, to try his Pulſe this way: Our young Shop-keeper, perhaps at firſt ſeems to pauſe on the matter, whilſt <hi>Mr. Shark</hi> keeps his Eyes ſtedfaſtly fixed on him, without ſpeaking a word; at length the Young-man calling to mind that he had (if he be unmarried) promiſed to help him to a conſiderable Fortune, faintly demands how much will ſupply his preſent Occaſion; he tells him a ſlender ſum, becauſe this he intends to pay, that he may Wiredraw him in, for a greater: If he offers to lend it him, he ſeems to fly off, ſaying, nay Sir, I did not ſpeak upon that account, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, if it will incommode you, ſay ſo, and put your ſelf to no ſtraits for me, for I can have it elſewhere. You need but tell me, if it will be any Inconveniency to you, to ſpare it for a few days; I know ſome will be glad of the occaſion to ſerve me, but theſe are Favours only to be aſked of ſpecial Friends. Nay Sir, ſays the young
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:35213:21"/>Shop-keeper, I have Money by me, which is not due to pay, till ſuch a time, and it will be little Improvement to me to keep in my Till; therefore pray let me ſerve you with the Summ you deſire: This is accepted, a Treat given, and punctually pay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed at the time prefixed; but ſoon after, upon ſuch a pretence, a double Sum or more is laid upon him: And if that way prevails not, then he inviting the young Shop-keeper abroad, in the midſt of their jol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity, when he has Drank him to a Pitch, the Drawer comes up, and whiſpers <hi>Mr. Shark,</hi> that there are three Men enquire for him, and will have no deny<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al, but are coming up Stairs; at this, he by keep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in his Breath, and ſtraining, forces himſelf to change Colour, then bites his Lip, and layes his Hand on his Sword; which ſuddain alteration, the young man perceiving, earneſtly enquires into the Cauſe, when with a ſigh he replyes, was ever any Gentleman ſo affronted? now ſhall I be Arreſted for 500 <abbr>
                     <hi>l.</hi>
                  </abbr> and nothing ſo much grieves me, but it will happen in your Company; were it not for bringing you into trouble, I would ſcour theſe Rogues to the Devil and farther; theupon half drawing his Sword, in the mean while the pretended Officers and Cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditor enter the Room, and a Sham-ſcuffle begins, but <hi>Mr. Shark</hi> at length ſurrenders, in reſpect, as he ſays, to his dear Friend, that he may come to no harm among ſuch Villians: Then they begin to Treat, the Creditor owns the money has been due but a little while, but his craving Neceſſities forced him to this Ungentile Action; he will be willing to take part, and Bond for the reſt, with Security; and ſo huſh up the Matter, that it ſhall not redound to his Diſgrace, for he knows he is about a great Fortune. Then <hi>Mr. Shark</hi> wiſhfully looking on his Companion, in a piteous Tone, aſks if he will be ſo
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:35213:21"/>kind in this Matter, proteſting he has a Thouſand Pound to receive in ten days, left him by an Uncle lately dead. The Young man perhaps Humms and Haws a little at firſt, as being ſurpriſed and ſtun'd with this Novel Accident: but upon freſh Intreaties and Promiſes, that he ſhall not be damaged by it, the value of a pins-point, between willing and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>willing he conſents, if he has ten or twenty Guine is about him, that's layed down in part; if not, what he has ſuffices; and <hi>Mr. Shark</hi> adds to it what his Pockets afford, and a joint Bond is given for the reſt, but made payable in a very ſhort time, leſt the Vil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lany ſhould be diſcovered; for this is no other, than a Confederacy between them, and when the Money is paid, the Sham-Officer and Creditor, have a ſmall ſhip out of it, for Midwiſing this Plot of <hi>Mr. Sharks</hi> begetting.</p>
               <p>Our Sham-Creditor knows his day of payment, as well as a Racking Landlord, thoſe of the four Quarters of the Year, and goes punctually to the Young-man for it; which ſtartles him: For <hi>Mr. Shark</hi> to carry on farther his Correſpondence, told him the debt was paid, Bond taken up, Cancell'd and Burnt; but ſeeing his Hand againſt him, and not having pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared the Money, is in a peek of troubles. Mr. <hi>Shark</hi>'s Counſel is now wanting, for he abſconds 'till the bluſter is over. If he can borrow of Friends, or on Plate, Rings, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> to raiſe the Sum, it goes no farther; if not, the threats of a Goal makes him run upon Extreams, either preſently to ſhut up, or go down into the Country to ſee his Uncle or what is worſe, ſign a warrant of Attorney, to Enter up Judgement, without thinking of taking a Defei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zance; and all is ſeized, himſelf put to ſhift, if he eſcapes ſo, and his real Creditors cheated. If in this Extremity, to prop up his Credit, he flatters
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:35213:22"/>himſelf to lean on his Siſters Portion, by borrowing it of her, he is there likewiſe diſappointed; for upon Enquiry, ten to one ſhe is wheedled on't, or clandeſtinely Married to one of <hi>Sharks</hi> Shabby Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panions, who decoyed her with the flattering hopes of being a Lady; for ſhe was aſſured by <hi>Shark,</hi> he was a Knight, and his Eſtate in ſuch a County, worth 5000 <hi>per Annum;</hi> kept his Coach, and many other fine things: and this Marriage he told her, muſt be celebrated without the knowledge of any of her neareſt Relations, leſt the Knight too long de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>layed, ſhould fly off; and indeed the poor innocent Girl, by Mr. <hi>Shark</hi>'s appointment, ſtealing to a <hi>Spring-Garden</hi> Entertainment, eager to poſſeſs Loves delici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Fruits, fond, and over perſwaded, the Marriage was huddled up upon little more than meer Recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendation, fancying a Man, her wiſe Brother had often prais'd in her hearing, as the beſt, and moſt cordial of his Friends, would never be ſo baſe, as to betray the Siſter unto a miſerable Misfortune; when aſhamed of ſuch a Viſionary Love, by Advice, and her own Inclination, ſhe concluded to keep her Marriage ſecret, till a more favourable Opportunity to reveal it; but this unlucky Accident, extorted more early, than elſe ſhe would have diſcloſed it, and one happineſs in the midſt of Miſery, our young Shop-keeper may comfort himſelf in, <hi>viz.</hi> That he had not a Street-trotting Crack impoſed on him, inſtead of a huge Fortune: And this was declined not ſo much for his ſake, as that they were reſolved to ſhare his Fortune amongſt them, without taking in any more Partners, where theſe Devices are not practicable, and frequently they hit; but our <hi>Shark</hi> has other ways; <hi>viz.</hi> to ruin our Youngſter by prompting him on to Gaming, Whoring and Expenſiveneſs, and when he is forced to hide his Head, he pretending all the
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:35213:22"/>Sorrow in the World for his Misfortune, undertake privately to convey his Goods away in the Night-s time, to a truſty Friend of his, who has a conve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niency to ſtow them; which if agreed to, and cle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verly got off, they are ſold out by piece-meal, and the Owner has the leaſt Share: When all is gone, and no more can be expected, to prevent our Youngſter's hanging on him, or being troubleſom to him in his Neceſſity, <hi>Mr. Shark</hi> frights him to Sea, by laying before him the terrible Idea of a Gaol, repreſenting it far worſe than it is, though bad enough; or elſe, which is yet more, for a ſmall matter betrays him, into the hands of his Creditors, who hurry him into one of the City poud'ring-Tubs, and will have no Compaſſion on him in his languiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; becauſe in his Proſperity he would have none of himſelf, but give way to his Folly, that thruſt him head-long on his Misfortunes. And indeed our <hi>Town-Shark,</hi> keeps up the Humour of his Folly by many Devices, leſt his Underſtanding, which he cauſes to be locked up in a dark Cellar, all the time he deals with him, ſhould get looſe, and fru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate his Deſign; if he underſtands ſober People have given him Advice, tending to his Good, in reclaiming, and bringing himſelf within Bounds, he inveighs and exclaims againſt them, as too cenſori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, and Enemies to Youthful Pleaſure, becauſe grown old, or wanting the advantage, they cannot purſue them; and never leaves, till he ſets him at variance with them; or if this is beyond his power, he will Pipe, Drink, Fiddle, and ſing their grave Counſel out of his Thoughts, and with a Whirlwind raiſed, by breathing Oaths and the direſt Impre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cations of his Cordial Friendſhip, and ſincerity to do him Good, blow it to the Land of Oblivion. If the Young man at any time deſires his Company to
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:35213:23"/>viſit, any of his grave or ſober Relations, he will de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cline it, pretending he has not time, or is indiſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed; but his fear is, they ſhould unmaſk him, and lay open to him his fallacies, by diſſolving the Charm, and letting him ſee e're it be too late, what he has to truſt to.</p>
               <p>If our <hi>Shark</hi> has brought a young Beginner to a declining condition, but there is ſomething remain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, whereby he expects ſome further advantage, to keep him from Starting, he gravely admoniſhes him, with much ſeeming concern for his ſinking ſtate, to enter himſelf a Priſoner in the <hi>Fleet,</hi> or <hi>Kings-Bench;</hi> telling him, the Marſhal or Warden, or their Clarks are his intimate Friends, and for a little Money (for ſays he, you may very well con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceit among Gaol-keepers, there is not much Civility to be expected without it) he will get him to be a Priſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner at large; and then a Fig for his Creditors, &amp; their Catch-Poles; and perhaps the Young-man grievi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly peſtered, with a parcel of Civility-Varlets, hearkens to this, and gives him his own Reckoning, which is twice as much, as he has bargained for, on his behalf. But this will not do, for the Creditors ſeeing themſelves thus like to be cheated, if he eſcapes a Statute, are eager to ſue him to Execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; he tells <hi>Mr. Shark</hi> of this, and that the next Term he expects it, aſking his Advice, who putting on a grave Countenance, and ſhaking his Noddle, ſolemnly proteſts he knows not what to think on it; he did not imagin they would be ſo haſty, but if it comes to Execution, he cannot warrant him, but that he may be ſent for in, and made a cloſe Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoner: And perhaps if the Wind blows ſo hard in that Corner, there may be Statutute of Bankrupt in it, for ought he knows: And therefore in ſober-ſadneſs, he adviſes him to Knock off in time, make
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:35213:23"/>the moſt of what he has, and away to <hi>Ireland,</hi> where he may Set-up again out of their reach, with the Money he ſhall raiſe, or fall into other Buſineſs, promiſing to aſſiſt; and that it muſt be done ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretly. This done, <hi>Mr. Shirk</hi> divides and chooſes, then they part, the Young-man with real, and <hi>Mr. Shirk</hi> with feigned Tears; the latter giving the former a Note of the chief Places, the diſtance of Miles, and what Inns he ſhall call at for the beſt En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertainment on the Road. And by this knowing what Stages he will make, loth that he ſhould carry ſo much Money away with him, he has not been many Hours departed, but he haſtens to the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhalſea or Warden, or to his Bail, if he had any, tells them their Priſoner is gone, and it may be gets a Guinea or two, to direct them how to ſend Hue and Cry after him; when poor Peel-garlick, by this unexpected Diſcovery being purſued, taken, and brought back, is cloſe confined to hard-meat, but is ignorant who was the Informer. In his Miſery he ſends for <hi>Mr. Shirk,</hi> who condoles his Condition, and in a little time eaſes him of his Money, upon ſpecious Promiſes to get his Liberty the ſecond time, or Compound with his Creditors, but does nothing in either Caſe: And no more being expected from Friends or otherwiſe, our <hi>Shirk</hi> who had all this while, chattered to his proſperity, finding the Winter of Adverſity come upon him, leaves him, and flies to a warmer Sun, whilſt our deluded Young-man, having his Eyes opened by ſad Experience, ſees too late, by what ſiniſter means he came into this deplorable Condition, in which without Gods great mercy, he is like to end his days.</p>
               <p>One thing more I have to offer, and ſo I ſhall conclude this Chapter.</p>
               <p>One Villanous Trick, both the <hi>Town-ſhift</hi> and
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:35213:24"/>
                  <hi>Shirk,</hi> (for here I muſt join them,) put indiffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rently on Gentlemen and Trades-men, as they find opportunity, they uſe perſwaſion to inveigle them to Ride out of Town ten or twenty Miles, to take the Air; and rather than they will want his Compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny they have a deſign upon, a Horſe ſhall-be furniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed for him at their charge, with Boots, Holſters, Pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtols, Sword, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> ſo riding on very frolicſome, and ſporting with Paſſengers they meet on the Road, at laſt upon ſome turning or elbowing way, at a diſtance; one of them cryes yonder is an old Cormudgeon coming, let us take a frolick to fright him. Our Gentle-man or Trades-man in company, ignorant of what is intended, ſays perhaps little to the matter, and ſo they come cloſe up, when <hi>Shift</hi> or <hi>Shirk</hi> claps a Piſtol to the Mans Breaſt, and with an Oath bids him Deliver; whereupon he piteouſly cryes out, he is utterly undone, the reſt of the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany (except our Gentleman or Trades-man, who knows not what to think of it) laugh and Cry, let the old Rogue go, however, the other winking, as much as to ſay, he deſigns to fright him more, fum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles, and ſearches him, and in a ſlight ſtruggling this ſuppoſed Country-man, (a Fellow of their Gang, ſent thither in that diſguiſe) on purpoſe to watch their coming tumbles from his Horſe, roars out lamentably of the bruiſe he has received, but more piteouſly cryes, he's undone, he's undone; whereat whipping his Horſe to drive him a diſtance from his, they leave him in that pickle, and ride away laughing as hard as they can drive; but this proves no laughing Matter, to our young Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man or Trades-man in the end; for this Sham-Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try-man has notice where he lives, ſoon finds him out, charges him as one of the Highway-men that robbed him, threatning and Hectoring at ſuch a rate,
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:35213:24"/>that being conſcious of what they termed a Frolick, and not knowing what to think of, or where to find them, and fearful of aſking Advice, his Reputation in that being at Stake, beſide the known danger of the Law, he finds himſelf conſtrained to comply with the Fellow's demands, to huſh up the matter. More of their Villanies I might enumerate under this Head, but theſe are a ſufficient reliſh.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. V.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>The lively Character of a <hi>Sharper,</hi> or ordinary <hi>Town-Shift.</hi> His ways to get acquainted with <hi>Shop-keepers Apprentices,</hi> and others; how he deludes them from their Buſineſs, brings them into bad Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany, Bubbles them of their Money, puts <hi>Jilting Strumpets,</hi> or <hi>Cracks</hi> of the Town, upon them; with other Miſchiefs, to the Ruin and Diſgrace of many of them.</p>
               </argument>
               <p>IT cannot be denied, but Society is coveted and deſired by all; nothing in the Creation can be truly ſaid to be averſe to it. But how dangerous a thing it is to venture unadviſedly, too many know by ſad Experience; particularly, the giddy Younger ſort, whoſe green Heads are not furniſhed with a ſound Judgment to diſcern what may be advanta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geous, and what deſtructive.</p>
               <p>It is not the multitude of Acquaintance, but the goodneſs of it, that is to be choſen and coveted; and it is impoſſible but he muſt be ſullied with-Vice, who crouds himſelf into Company at a venture.</p>
               <p>But what cares our <hi>Sharper</hi> with whom he aſſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciates, they can ſcarce be worſe than himſelf: he cares not a Pin what their Vices are, ſo he can
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:35213:25"/>extract his beſt Benefit from them; and if they are timorous, he ſtudies to make them vicious, that they may be more at his Devotion.</p>
               <p>His acquaintance with Youth, is the firſt Draught of thoſe he intends to ruin; he lays them down before him, as the foul Copy, before he can Write true and perfect: From hence, as from a Probation, he takes his Degree in their Reſpects, 'till at laſt he wholly poſſeſſes them; and by theſe means, impro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priates and incloſes to himſelf, what before lay in common.</p>
               <p>But to keep my Method through the whole Work, I now proceed to give the Reader ſome Account; who and what this <hi>Rake-Hell</hi> is, before I proceed to his wicked Practices on Youth.</p>
               <p>He is a Fellow, as the reſt, pretending to Great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of Birth; and to back the Reputation he would force from hence, is ever babbling of his Rich Rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, whom he places too remote for any one to trouble himſelf about an Enquiry. Though his Name agreeing with ſome Pariſh or other, makes it preſumed he was dropt by ſome ſtrowling Beg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gar or canting Gipſy; and drag'd up by a blear-ey'd Nurſe, 'till he was able to ſhew her and his Bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>factors a fair pair of Heels; as being frighted away with the Bugbear of being put Apprentice to ſome ſcurvy Trade: for the thoughts of Labour turns his Stomach, makes him ſicken, and is worſe he fears than a Diſeaſe, or a fit of the Stone.</p>
               <p>The firſt thing he pitches upon, being now deſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute of Friends and a Habitation, is to liſt, and ſeaſon himſelf among the <hi>Black-Guard;</hi> becoming very induſtrious at his Entrance, to learn their Rogueries, in Filching, Managing the Dey, Luck<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in-a-Bag, Pricking at the Girdles, Hocus-Pocus, and the various Tricks and Stratagems of a <hi>Sweetner.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="47" facs="tcp:35213:25"/>
               <p>The next thing is, to learn Bawdy Songs, and by herding among the St. <hi>Giles</hi>'s Scrapers; for Pots of Ale, he is taught ſome lamentable Tunes on the Violin; and his converſation with Foot-boys who wait for their Maſters at corners of Streets, gives him an opportunity to practiſe on the Flute, or ſuch-like Wind-Inſtrument. And to ſute himſelf more to the Humours of the Times, if poſſible, he procures in ſome blind Alehouſe or other haunted by that Nation, a little ſmattering of <hi>French.</hi> And now he thinks himſelf ſet up, were not a Genteel Sute of Cloaths wanting, the better to introduce him into the company of thoſe he deſigns to practiſe on. For this Supply, he does not long cudgel his Brains, ere an Opportunity offers it ſelf to ſupply that Defect. He ſaunters about <hi>Weſtminſter</hi> and St. <hi>James</hi>'s, 'till he ſees a Nobleman's or Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man's Door open, and the Paſſage clear as far as he has a proſpect; then having a Letter ſuperſcribed to ſome unknown Perſon; he firſt peeps about him, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hen boldly enters, and ſoftly trips up Stairs: if he be met or diſcovered, he enquires for ſuch a Gentleman, holding his Letter in his Hand; and no ſuch Man being known, he humbly begs Pardon for his boldneſs, and believes he is miſtaken in the Houſe, but is ſure he lives ſomewhere thereabouts. But if the Coaſt be clear, and any Doors open, a Camlet-Cloak, rich Morning-Gown, Plate, or what of value he can light on, is his Prize; and he ſoon finds a Broker to take off his Hands at a little more than half the Value, well gueſſing how he came by it; and knowing now it's offered, he dares not but take what they bid him, for fear they ſhould ſtop it in their Hands, and make out a Writ of Enquiry, that it may come the knowledge of the true Owner. With this Money he equips himſelf pretty tolera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly;
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:35213:26"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="47" facs="tcp:35213:26"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="48" facs="tcp:35213:27"/>and perhaps to perfect his Accoutrements, adds ſome little of his own, got at <hi>In and In,</hi> or <hi>Higheſt Loweſt, Jack and the Game,</hi> &amp;c. Thus well rigg'd he ſtrowls the City, and there fortune, as he terms it, throws in his way ſome Renegado from his Trade; one that is reſolved to be wicked, mangre all the Good of his Maſter and Relations; he finds him a fit Inſtrument to join with, and ſo they become ſworn Brethren in Iniquity. He uſes this unthinking Bubble as his Decoy, to allure ſome Apprentices of his Acquaintance into his company; magnifying him to them, as the moſt accompliſhed Man he ever met withal, and that his Converſation is ſo facetious and charming, that they cannot better divert themſelves than in it; eſpecially when Buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs ceaſes, and gives place to their Evening-Recreation; promiſing they ſhall have Singing and Muſick to entertain them, if a convenient Place can be appointed, free from Diſcovery.</p>
               <p>This Bait, no doubt, ſome of them preſently nibble at, not diſcerning the fatal Hook it covers, 'till ſtruck; and a Place is appointed to meet in the Evening: our <hi>Shift</hi> has notice of it from his Renegado-Scout, and fails not to come, provided with his Implements, dreſſed in the Beauiſh Faſhion: his <hi>Carolina</hi> laced, pinched up in three Corners; his long Wig poudered, and Coat Mealed to the ſmall of his Back. And being ſure to be at the prefixed Place, firſt leaves a Number at the Bar, which thoſe that come to him may ask for; the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> trips up Stairs, and requeſts the Drawer (who follows him) to ſhew the privateſt Room, remoteſt from Noiſe and Company, for his Buſineſs requires it. Promiſing him as Encouragement, if he draw good Wine, ſomething over and above the Reckoning, that will fall to his Share. The Room ſhewn, he
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:35213:27"/>enters, and takes his place at the upper end of the Table, calls for a Flask, and ſits humming to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, 'till the Youngſters drop in one by one, and are a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>l received by him with profound Ceremony and Reſpect; ſpeaking little, 'till his Scout comes in, who waits on the Stairs the while, to direct the Youngſters as they come up; that they may not miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take the Room, bolt into other Company unawares, or be ſeen by ſuch as may inform their Maſters or Parents. For under this Head I compriſe not only Apprentices, but Youths that are under the Tuition of their Friends: for this Haggard flyes at both. When no more are expected at this time, the Intro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducer or Petty Maſter of the Ceremonies makes an Harangue to them, how exceeding glad he is to ſee ſo many of his Croneys, giving them a hearty Wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come, and bidding them to be merry.</p>
               <p>Then our <hi>Shift</hi> taking up the Glaſs, turns off a Brimmer to their Proſperity, and ſo paſſes it about. And when it has pretty well gone round, their Spirits beginning to be exhilerated with the Juice of the Grape, he makes an Apology, that for his Friend's ſake, he being altogether a Stranger to them, he is made ſo happy as to be bleſſed with their good Company; and that if any thing lies in him to ſerve them, now or any other time, they may not only requeſt, but command it. Then changes his Diſcourſe, and falls upon an Encomium, praiſing the Youth of the City, as the Prop and Ornament of it; and uſes all his Stock of Flattery, to ſwell them with a Conceit of their Parts and Abilities; whil'ſt they ſit liſtening with their Mouths at half-cock, in a ſteady attention to his fallacious Dialect; being ſtruck to admiration with his fine way of Speaking: and from that time, they think him a Perſon well educated, and of Parts and Learning.</p>
               <pb n="50" facs="tcp:35213:28"/>
               <p>When he perceives he has gained a Point, he makes a full ſtop, ſits ſilent a while, and then drinks about; which done, his Companion perſwades him to give them a Tune or two, on his Flute, or Haut-boy, which he readily agrees to; then pulling out ſome Songs ſet to Muſick, though he knows not the Notes; to bear them in hand he ſings them, looking on his paper: After that, ſo feed their Curioſity farther, out comes <hi>Jack-in-a-box,</hi> and other Imple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, uſed in the Art of <hi>Hocus-pocus,</hi> or <hi>Leger-de-main;</hi> and by ſlight of Hand, ſeems to do Miracles, appearing to them no leſs, than a topping Conjurer, or dealer in the Black Art: So that much taken with the Man, their Hearts grow open, and after whiſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring together, one is deputed to ſtep down and order a Treat, that they may in ſome meaſure grati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie him, for his civil Obligements, and at parting will not ſuffer him to pay a Farthing, though he draws his Money, and earneſtly preſſes to do it, whilſt his Eye is on their hands, to ſee who draws moſt Money; for it is a Vanity in Youth on ſuch occaſions, in oſtentation to pull out all they have about them at once, and make a rattling with it, though there be but a trifle to pay: Nor does he forget to aſk what 'tis a clock, pretending ſome ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointment he has made, to meet a Friend, or an Aſſignation with a Lady, whom for the World he would not diſappoint; when the main drift of it is, to ſee how they are accommodated, with Watches, at this time no Gaming is propoſed, unleſs they propoſe it themſelves, and then he ſeems to diſap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove it, or put it off to a more ſeaſonable oppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunity, becauſe it will waſte more time, that at pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent it will be convenient perhaps for them; but eſpecially for him to ſpare: And the reaſon that moves him ſo to do is, becauſe he keeps this in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve,
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:35213:28"/>till he can ſingle them one by one, and bubble them to his greater advantage: And ſo at this time they break up, appointing the next meeting, and every one departs highly ſatisfied, no Complements being ſpared on either hand.</p>
               <p>After two or three General Meetings he becomes intimately acquainted with them, knows all their Names, and the Places of their Abode; and now it is his Buſineſs to ſingle them out, that his De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigns may be carried on more cloſe and cunningly, and that with celerity, that they may not have time to take Air; and concluding he has no far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther uſe for his Tool or Implement of a <hi>Renegado Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prentice</hi> he firſt wrought withal, but proving a Hang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er on, he may become troubleſom and dangerous, his next buſineſs is to ſhut his hands of him; and can propoſe to himſelf no ſurer way, than by pack<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing him to one of the Plantations, for that will pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce two Advantages, <hi>viz.</hi> To hinder his telling Tales, and making a Prize of him. This reſolved on, he profeſſes a world of Friendſhip to him, boaſts that he has been a great Traveller, and how plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant it is to be abroad; commends the Civility and Good Nature of Forreigners to the Skies, and what great Eſtates and Preferments Young-men have got abroad, who at home were deſtitute of Friends and Habitations: then perceiving the Cully attentive to what he ſayes, he demands if he be willing to Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vel, and he will help him to a Merchants Service, who will entertain him at Fifty Pounds a Year, his Horſe, and good Table, to be Overſeer of a Planta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: Our Youngſter being caſt off by his Friends for his lewd way of Living, and the Tricks he has played to to their prejudice and diſgrace, and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt weary of a Raking Life, attended with Want, ten to one hearkens to this; if he does, his next
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:35213:29"/>Buſineſs is to look out for a Maſter-Kidnapper, who is to repreſent the Merchant, he is bound by Inden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, but with ſolemn promiſes of Freedom: only this is a complying with the Law, for otherwiſe, if ſearch be made, it would obſtruct his paſſage: and thus being underhand for a ſmall matter, he is wood-cocked into Slavery, to repent at leiſure his Folly, in not knowing when he was well in the Eſteem of his Friends, and placed with a good Maſter, with whom had he ſerved out his Time, it might have been the making of him for ever. If this way fail, he has another, which is to wheedle out of him, where he has run in Debt, and ſends one, for he will not be ſeen in it himſelf, to diſcover where he is, and perſwade his Creditors to put him in Gaol, aſſuring them, that then his Friends will compaſſionate him, pay his Debts, and take him. And by this Treachery he is laid up in Lavender, I know not how long, but un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doubtedly till our <hi>Shift</hi> has done his Work, without any danger of Obſtruction from him. If he be enquired after by any that hath been in their Company, he proteſts he has not ſeen him of late, and believes he is gone into the Country; for the laſt time he was with him, he talked that his Friends had ſent for him, and then he intended to go down, to ſee what they would do on his behalf, in ſetting him in ſome Way.</p>
               <p>This the Coaſt being cleared, our <hi>Shift</hi> cull<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> out firſt thoſe that he thinks the ableſt, having the Confidence to go to the Shop; but if he ſees the Maſter, or any one that is apt to take notice, he aſks for ſomebody he thought, as he ſays, had lodg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed there, or for ſome Goods he knows they have not to ſell, winking at the Young-man to talke no notice of him; but watches his opportunity when the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter's back is turned, to ſlide a Note, which he has
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:35213:29"/>always ready on ſuch Emergencies, into the Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prentices hand, to let him know where he ſhall meet him in the Evening; and not to bring any with him, becauſe he has ſomething of Importance to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe him about; when they meet, he embraces him with abundance of kindneſs, aſſuring him he is the Favorite of Fortune, and his Stars ſmile upon him; when the Young-man demands what he means by theſe Expreſſions, he bids him call to remembrance, if he did not ſee a Coach ſtay before his Maſter's Door ſuch a Day, and about ſuch an Hour: Upon this pauſeing a little, he replies he did; why, ſays he, in that Coach there was a handſom, rich, young Lady, who ſeeing you ſtanding at the Door, fixed her Eyes on you ſteadfaſtly, do you remember any thing of that? It might be ſo, replies our Appren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice, I think, to the beſt of my remembrance, there was a Woman in it, but I did not mind her Eyes; well, 'tis no matter, ſays he, whither you did or not, but ſhe ſo well noted your comely Features and Perſon, that by all ſigns and tokens, as I am infor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med by her Waiting Gentlewoman, ſhe is fallen deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perately in Love with you; and if it comes to ſo hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py a buſineſs as Marriage, you are made for ever; the Sign, Trade and Deſcription anſwers: But I would not have you confuſe your Thoughts about it, till I enquire into farther Particulars, and then if I can be any ways aſſiſting to bring you together, you ſhall find me a ſincere and Cordial Friend: For as I underſtand, though Love, has got the Maſtery, yet being a Virgin, and but young, her Bluſhes, and Shame of ſuch a Viſionary-Love, that took her flying as it were, there will be ſome difficulty (ſhould you be admitted a Viſit) to bring her to own her paſſion for you, till time and your ſervices give her an ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable Opportunity.</p>
               <pb n="54" facs="tcp:35213:30"/>
               <p>Our Youngſter now in his hot Blood, tickles his Fancy at this, though but a feigned Story, to draw Preſents from him, which he pretends to hand to her Gentlewoman, who is his intimate Acquaintance; the better to make his Letter he ſends with them acceptable, and exact an Anſwer from the fair One. If the Young-man is not over-credulous in this mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, he has many Stories at his Tongues-end, taken out of Novels and Romances, that Loves irreſiſtible Power has compelled Queens to lay their Diadems at the Feet of Shepherds; and great Princeſſes who might have had Kings with Kingdoms to their Dow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, to doat on a Slave. But the Preſents and Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter are not required, till he firſt ſee the Lady; yet it muſt be at a diſtance, and as if by chance, and no ſpeaking to her, the firſt time at leaſt. In the mean while, he rooks Money out of him, to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compliſh him in playing on the Flute, Violin, Sing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, to make a Courtlike Addreſs, and Compliment alamode; that his Parts and Knowledge Abeing im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proved, he may be the fitter Match for a Lady: And all this while the Young-man treats high, however he pinches to come by it, and rarely they part with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Gaming, which drains his Pockets; but what cares he, this great Match will abundantly recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pence: And for Diet and other Neceſſaries, there needs no Money to purchaſe that, for he knows who is bound to provide it for him.</p>
               <p>If his Stock at any time fails, he can borrow of neighbouring Apprentices, and many times they have a common Stock amongſt them, to ſupply ur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent neceſſities. The Love-Story ſtill running in the Young-Man's Mind, hoping by ſuch means to be his own Maſter before his Time is expired, has the Ladies fancied Idea in his Mind ſleeping and waking, and is as often deluded with pleaſing Dreams.
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:35213:30"/>But being often put off with delays of knowing who ſhe is, or ſeeing of her, he grows ſo impatient, that his ſuppoſed Friend is forced to promiſe him a ſight of her, leſt he ſhould think himſelf deluded, and fall off before he has accompliſhed his ends; yet can ſet him no Day then, but the next time he comes, tells him he now can make him happy in his deſires, that he may have a full view of her to his Hearts content; for her Gentlewoman informed him, ſhe goes this very Evening to divert her Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lancholy at the Play-houſe in — her place in one of the Boxes, and he knowing her, can eaſily ſhow him which is ſhe, if he will prepare to go thither: Our Youngſter's heart leaps within him at this Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, dreſſes himſelf ſpruce, and wants not a pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence to get leave to go out for an hour or two.</p>
               <p>Being in the Pit, which coſts our Young-man Five Shillings, for on this bleſſed Occaſion he can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not refuſe paying for both. Our <hi>Shift</hi> watches as the Ladies come in, to take their Seats, and eſpying one young, gay and beautiful, he claps our Young-man about the Neck, and whiſpers him, that's ſhe who came in laſt or middlemoſt, deſcribing her Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bit, that he may not miſtake, then all Play-time he minds neither Actors nor Muſick, his Eyes are fixt on the charming Fair; and if ſhe caſts her Eye on him, as likely ſhe does by chance, as well as upon others, this heightens his Joyes, puts him into Tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſports and Raptures, and from this time firmly be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieves all that was told him: ſo that perhaps he really falls in Love, and doats on a Lady that per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps is Married; which neither he nor his Fellow knows where to find: However, under this umbrage he is rooked of his Money, and perhaps of more than his own, ſends a letter full of endearing Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſions, with as rich a Preſent as he can make,
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:35213:31"/>and has a forged or counterfeit anſwer, if not at the firſt, yet certainly at the ſecond ſending, in ſomewhat doubtful Terms, yet hinting the recep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of his Preſents, and promiſing a ſutable Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn. But not to dwell too long on this Matter, when he has dreined him of all his Money, Goods, Wearing Apparel, which he obliges him to take up of his Taylor, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and ſees there is little more coming; or that the Young-man thus deluded, begins to ſmell a Rat, he drops off; and leaves him to ſeek this Lady in the Clouds, where he can find her; which if he happens to do, he will be never the wiſer, for ſhe is altogether ignorant of the Matter; and if he ſhould be ſo fooliſh to make any preſumptuous Pretenſions, confiding what he told him is real, he may happen to get a good Drubbing, be Toſſed in a Blanket, or worſe uſed; as I knew one ſerved not long ſince, who built on the ſame Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation.</p>
               <p>Our <hi>Shift</hi> has many other Devices to enſnare Young-men: If he perceives they are not Amo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous one way, he attacks them another; if Marriage charm not, he has a Crack in a corner for him, whom he calls Couſin, by whoſe aſſiſtance he chains them to him, or entangles them ſo faſt in the Net of Flattery and Deceit, till he can pluck their Plumes: He denies not but ſhe is a Married Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, though indeed there is nothing in it; but this by another Statagem ſerves a turn, for ſhe being very <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ocoſe, and familiar, one or other of the Youngſters he brings her acquainted with, will puſh on for a Favour, as he fooliſhly terms it, but ſhe in the midſt of yeilding, puts on a Coy Look, with what do ye mean by this rudeneſs? Will ſtruggle, and pretends on a ſuddain, all the unwillingneſs in the World; if ſhe picks not his Pocket, ſhe will be ſure
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:35213:31"/>to get his Pocket-book, or ſomething that is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>markably known to be his, which perhaps at that time he miſſes not, nor does ſhe give him time to do it; for in a great huff, with Threats and bent Brows, ſometimes forcing Tears, which ſhe has at com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand, ſhe flings away; and if a <hi>Bully-Rock,</hi> pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tending to be her Huſband, enter not preſently with a Sham-Conſtable and Warrant, to demand Satisfaction for the Abuſe done to his Wife; to be ſure within a Day or two the Youngman is ſent for to the Tavern, hemn'd in by two or three grim look'd Fellows, charged with the rude Abuſe which has made the Woman Miſcarry, and endangered her Life; then threatned, with abundance of hard Words, mingled with dire Imprecations; if he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny it, they produce what ſhe took from him, as a demonſtrable Witneſs: So that at legth not know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing what to ſay or think of the matter, he propo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, to ſave his Reputation, and the farther danger he may incur, an Accommodation, and ſo they fleece him of his ready Money, Rings, Watch, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> but theſe wanting, if of Age, they take ſomething in part, and bring him into Bond, which they have ready, to fill up themſelves; for they are as fraid to have it known, as he is; for that they are ſure will ſpoil their Market. If this ſeems to be the laſt Stake, then <hi>Mr. Shift</hi> leaves our Youngſter; if not, when he hears of it, he rages, raves and ſtorms at a prodigious rate, vowing they ſhall repent putting ſuch a Trick upon his Friend: Then by degrees growing milder, begins to chide the Youngman for being ſo unadviſedly raſh; when the truth is, he went away and left them together, to no other end then to bring this about: And if before it was made up he had been ſought to mediate the matter, it would have been as hard to have found him, as a
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:35213:32"/>Needle in a Bottle of Hay; for he abſented his Lodging, and diſguiſed himſelf, not to be found; and indeed it behoved him, ſince he laid the Plot, and comes in for two Thirds of the Profit.</p>
               <p>Sometimes there is another Stratagem of this na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture in the wind, though the Youngman frolicks on a Barren Heath where nothing will grow; yet the ſubtil Female will in a little time appear pregnant with a Cuſhion, and ſending for him to a Tavern or ſome other more convenient place, with a He or She confident to back the Deſign, and calls her Siſter, upon his firſt approach with, a feigned Paſſion will burſt into Tears, ſobbing and ſighing under her Hood for a pretty ſpace, whilſt the Youngman ſtands in admiration, what ſhould cauſe this ſudden Paſſion, and who this ſhould be; doubtful whither to advance or retreat, the Diſſembling Sorrowful Crack Companion intreats him to ſit down, and ſhutting the Door, carefully liſtens, as to be infor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med if any be near, and then in a grave ſet Speech begins, Sir, do not you know my Siſter here? And when he proteſts he does not; well, continues he or ſhe, you did once, to her Shame and the Diſgrace of our Family, never ſtained before; though now perhaps you would willingly blot her out of your remembrance: But that ſhall not excuſe you, nor ſerve your turn, hold up your head <hi>Betty,</hi> and let the Gentleman ſee your Face more plainly, to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>freſh his treacherous Memory; nay never bluſh for the matter, what's done cannot be recalled: But one would have thought you might have been wiſer before this had happened: Upon this our ſeemingly diſtreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Damſel riſes, wipes her Eyes, uncovers her Face, and ſhews ſomething like a great Belly, and with a Sigh ſays, Sir do you not know me? I am ſure by woful Experience I have cauſe to know you, and
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:35213:32"/>ſhall to the laſt moment of my Life. What, you cannot call me to remembrance I'l warant, now I wiſh I had never ſeen your Eyes, nor you mine: And then ſhe falls to weeping and wringing her Hands, Well well, ſays her Confident, this is no jeſting matter, never mince it, you know my Siſter well enough; you were introduced by ſuch a one as a Lover, but like an ungentile Wretch as you are, over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>powering the poor Creature with Drink, that baſe Man withdrawing, and leaving you together, you rudely played a wild Freak; ſee Sir, pointing to her Belly, the effect of your Frolickſomneſs: There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore to be ſhort, either Marry my Siſter, to repair her loſt Honour, and in ſome manner, blot out the Stain you have caſt on our Family; or we will make not only the City, but all <hi>England</hi> too hot to hold you.</p>
               <p>The Youngman now calling ſomething of the Face before him, to mind; and remembring his Fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, ſtands as one Thunder-ſtruck, amazed and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>founded, not knowing what to reply; whilſt the pretended Siſter enumerates what Matches ſhe might have had, and what mighty Fortunes this has hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered her of; and to be brief, if he have any thing of an Eſtate, they terrify him, for want of taking better Counſel, into a ruinous and fatal Marriage; if not, which moſtly ſucceeds, he ſtrains himſelf by all the ways he can (it matters not to them whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, lawful or unlawful) to give her a preſent Sum of Money, with a Bond or ſolemn Promiſe to maintain the Child at Nurſe, if it lives; leaſt his Friends knowing it, he ſhould be Diſinherited, or caſt out of their Favour, and the whole redound to his perpetual Diſgrace; and ſo for the preſent it is laid aſleep, but at length comes a Bill for the Charges of her Lying-in, and a Child is borrowed of
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:35213:33"/>a conniving Nurſe, and produced, whoſe Nurſing he muſt be content to pay for, though he got not one, nor ſhe never had any, or he conceits worſe will follow: And out of this, his ſuppoſed Friend has a conſiderable Snack.</p>
               <p>Theſe are not all the Intrigues to bubble Young-men, and gull them out of their Money; for ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times walking together, Sweeteners are laid by appointment in their way, who purpoſely drop Money or Braſs-Rings gilded, and ſuddenly taking them up, as if realy found, our Hawks-eyed <hi>Shift</hi> ſteps forward, and cryes halves Gentlemen, you have found ſomething, and it is but reaſonable we ſhould ſee what it is; nay, ſays one of the Sweet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, if you ſee me take it up, it is but fair you ſhould: Then it is produced, perhaps Half-a-Crown, Half-Guinea, or a Ring, if the firſt or ſecond, one of the Stweeteners propoſes to go to ſuch a Houſe, and there divide it equally over a Pot of Beer, Ale or a Glaſs of ſuch as the Houſe affords: For ſince they had ſuch good luck in accidentally jumping together, it is all the reaſon in the World, they ſhould not part with dry Lips. Our Youngſter is ſoon allured to accompany them, ſeeing his ſuppoſed Friend very forward in the matter, and ſo haſts as a Bird to the Snare. The Houſe entred, and Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quor called called for, the Money is punctually di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided; and the Glaſs or Mugg goes merrily round, till one riſing to Piſs, finds where he or his Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panion had placed it; a Pack of Cards, or a Box with Dice in ſome odd Corner, and ſhewing them to the Company, ſays here has been Gamſters I ſee, and what harm would it be, if we ſhould play a Game to paſs away half an Hour or ſo; we cannot have better Drink any where. To this Motion our Youth ſays little, and our <hi>Shift</hi> appearingly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clines
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:35213:33"/>it, pretending haſty Buſineſs; but the other two, for they always hunt in Couples, engage, but Play very awkardly, as if they were Novices at Gaming; whereupon our <hi>shift</hi> whiſpers our Young-man, ſaying, if he will go his halves, he will take them up, ſeeing they are ſo eager for Play, and doubts not but to make a Penny of them; urg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing their Ignorance as the main reaſon that incites him to it: So upon the wink, one of them on the loſing hand, throws up and ſays he will play no more, for he finds Fortune jilts him at this time, though at others ſhe has been conſtant to him: Then our <hi>Shift</hi> takes up the Conqueror, and wins many ſmall Stakes, then his Adverſary as en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raged his Luck is changed, challenges him to double, vowing to win the Horſe or loſe the Saddle; and the Game at length running very high, the crafty Knave that before ſeemed to play nothing, turns luck, as he calls it; and our Youngſter, plyed with Bumpers till his Brains begin to Crow, to keep the Humour up, either by going halves, or ventu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring to revenge the loſs, himſelf is in the end ſtript; and when they ſee him turn his Pockets, and no more Money appears, they fleering whiſper, and ſay the Lamb is Bitten: His ſuppoſed Friend however to make him ſome amends, as he ſays, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he was partly the occaſion of the Loſs, pays his Shot, goes out with him in a Huff, ſwearing they are Cheats, and if he had but an Officer at hand, he would make them know it before he part<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with them: Upon this they retort, and bluſter at a high rate, ſo that the Young-man fearing a Quarrel may ariſe, and miſchief enſue, has his care leſſened, for the loſs of his Money, by the Joy he conceives of being got from them.</p>
               <p>If it happen to be a Ring or counterfeit Jewel,
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:35213:34"/>they pretend to find, they are not haſty to go to any Houſe, but it is ſhewed round and every one ſets his value on it, except our Youngſter, who confides in his treacherous Friend, who whiſpers him he is confident it is right, and if ſo, worth much more; and if he had Money enough about him, he would give them their Shares, ſend them packing, and be a conſiderable Gainer by the Bargain. Upon this the Young-man is incited to lay down the Money, it may be 20 <abbr>
                     <hi>s.</hi>
                  </abbr> for the value of Six-pence, and our <hi>Shift</hi> knowing where they rendezvous, comes in for his Share. If the Young-man offers it, and finds it a counterfeit, he complains the next meet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to our <hi>Shift,</hi> who pretends much Sorrow for his overſight, and proteſts he was never ſo deceived in his Life; but as for his Share, he is willing to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn it, but his Pockets at preſent will not ſpeak. However, at another time he ſhall have it in Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney, or a Treat, which he pleaſes; this is taken kindly, and ſo all is huſh between them.</p>
               <p>When he perceives our Youngſter pretty well drained, and not likely in ready <hi>Rino,</hi> to hold out much longer, the Harveſt being Reaped, he cares not to ſtay for the Leaſings, and therefore af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter many endearments, acquaints him he is to go into the Country to ſee his Rich Relations, and would willingly appear amongſt them like himſelf, but wants an Equipage; therefore if he knows any Mercer, Draper, Haberdaſher or Taylor that he can recommend him to, to New-Rig him, and paſs his word with him till his Return, which will be in a few Weeks, with a great ſum of Money he is to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive, left him as a Legacy by his Uncle, a Year paſt; and ſo long it muſt be, becauſe he would not have Mourning Cloaths, he will gratefully acknowledge it; and if the Young-man has ſuch an Intereſt, 'tis
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:35213:34"/>Ten to One but he makes uſe of it, though he muſt certainly pay it himſelf; for our <hi>Shift,</hi> at taking leave, making a ſmall Treat, grows bold, and bor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowing of him the little he his left, troops off, ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver to ſee him more, if he can help it; unleſs he hears he is reinſtocked, or well ſet up, and then he's doubtful, till he has ſent others to ſound him; leſt his Eyes being open, to ſee the many Cheats impoſed on him, he ſhould in deteſtation of his Folly and Extravagancy, ſeek Reparation, and ſet the blew Butter-fly on his; ?ſo that being forcibly crouded on the wrong ſide the door, he muſt be conſtrained to come to an Accompt before he can get out of the <hi>Compter,</hi> though many times it comes not to this, for the unfortunate Youth not able to bring his Maſters Caſt to a bearing, or even his Accompts, his Credit alſo cracked abroad; for ſhame and fear deſerts his Service, and thereupon in all likelihood is deſerted by his Relations, when they underſtand the cauſe of it; and ſo loft forlorn and miſerable, unleſs Fortune by a lucky Accident hand him into ſome Gentile Place or Employment, little expected. Much more might be ſaid on this Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject, but this being ſufficient to caution Appren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tices, and other Youngmen, to ſhun ſuch Vermin, who ſeek to prey upon them: I now proceed to give Advice to the Female Sex, eſpecially of the Younger ſort, who are in no leſs danger to tread on Snares, unleſs an extraordinary Prudence and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duct be a Precaution to them.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="chapter">
               <pb n="64" facs="tcp:35213:35"/>
               <head>CHAP. V.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>The Character of a <hi>Beau,</hi> with the Artifices be uſes to wheedle and skrew himſelf into the Company and converſation of young Ladies and Gentlewomen; how he manages the Intrigue to bring them to Ruin and Diſgrace, to farther his wicked Purpoſes; with ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious Reflections, and cordial Advice to the Female Sex on this Occaſion.</p>
               </argument>
               <p>IT muſt be acknowledged, that young Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>women cannot be altogether excuſed from being in ſome meaſure guilty of the Vanity of the Times, and not a little in Love with Affectation; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore before I come cloſe to my intended purpoſe, I ſhall, though it may appear ſome digreſſion, ſhew what they are. Theſe are not well to be divided, though I muſt not call them Twins, becauſe more properly Vanity may be taken for the Mother, and Affection for her darling Daughter: Vanity is the Sin and Affectation the Puniſhment; the firſt may be called the Root of Self-love, and the latter the Fruit. Vanity is never at its full growth, till it brancheth into Affectation, and then it is unluckily compleat for deſigning Men to build on, and brood a Ruin too great to be ſhaken off, but by the Fall of what ſupported it.</p>
               <p>As for thoſe that practiſe on Young Ladies and Gentlewomen, I ſhall briefly, according to my Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thod, give you the Character of one for all, which may give a clear inſight to the whole Knot of theſe Intriguing Diſſemblers.</p>
               <p>He is a younger Brother, whom his unkind Father dealt with, as <hi>Pharoah</hi> did with the Children of <hi>Iſrael;</hi> expecting he ſhould make Brick without
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:35213:35"/>Straw: that is, to live at home as a Gentleman, and leave him nothing to maintain his Gentility, when thruſt abroad: he hated, with the <hi>Iriſh-man,</hi> that his Son ſhould be a Trades-man, though of never ſo Gentile a Calling, for fear of murthering his Genti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity; not thinking that after his Deceaſe, the Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man muſt perhaps be converted into a Serving-man, and it is well if he be no worſe: So that the Pride of his Houſe hath undone him. What would any one now have this poor Gentleman do? his Father Dead, his Elder Brother's Old Suits and he are much alike in requeſt; he's caſt off with a little Money in his Purſe, that the Sight and Memory of him and his Father may periſh together. This makes him hate the Country, and to <hi>London</hi> he comes, in hopes to improve his Breeding, by learning the Modiſh-ways of the Town; but falling in with <hi>Sharpers,</hi> he is ſoon bubbled of the little Money he brought from home, yet learns Experience by it, and ſeeing it a thriveing Trade, reſolves by degrees to proceed to the practice of it; and to be the better ground<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in it, reſorts Ordinaries, Coffee-houſes and Lot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teries, where he overlooks and gathers ſomething from their Diſcourſe and Managment of Policies and Intrigues, Cheats, Wheedles, Culling, Shams, and the like; and leſt his Memory prove Treacherous when he has occaſion to uſe them, he notes them down in his Pocket-Book as <hi>Memorandums;</hi> furniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing himſelf over and above with Pleaſant Jeſts and Merry Tales; but for all this practiſing on Men, he frequently finds his Silly Banter turned on him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, and is often Buffooned and outw<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ed by thoſe he ſuppoſes to over-reach; which grates on his Sto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mach, and makes him conclude the Taſk too hard for his Underſtanding; but however, having ſcraped up a little Money at All-Fours, Cribbidge and ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turing
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:35213:36"/>a Kicking by Setting a Main, when he had not a Doit in his Pocket to anſwer it, if his Luck had failed; and ſo keeping up a pretty Jaunty Garb, Fortune at length throws him upon a <hi>French</hi> Dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing-Maſter, as full of Folly and Vanity as an Ape of Tricks, whoſe Buſineſs it is, as he calls it, to lend the Ladies the uſe of his Fool, to teach them the Alamode Complement, the Reverence, and Fantaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ick Humours of his Nation, which is, as he tells us, always to Change. This one <hi>Mamouchee</hi> brings him acquainted with the Women, and he ſoon finds their Blind-ſide, how much Flattery is pleaſing to them, and ſerves as Satan's Bellows, to blow up the leaſt Spark of Pride into a Flame; for having learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to Dance the Antick, he is for ſome time pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferred to be his Uſher, which over and above gets him large acquaintance with the Tender Sex; and his Study is next, how he may beſt Humour them, and ſo decoy them into misfortune.</p>
               <p>In his Diſcourſe he is carefull to avoid all rough and Beaſtly Language, and is not guilty of the Incor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rigible Folly of ſome whoſe Heads being full of Fire and Sword, batteries, Aſſaults, and Storming Towns; though perhaps they had as lieve hear the Devil as a Drum in War, and always were ſo tender of their Perſons, as never to come within Cannon-Shot; he concludes ſuch Diſcourſe rather frightens Tender hearted Ladies, than chains a Liſtening Attention; and rather makes them afraid, than give any deſire to ſeek his Converſation; and therefore takes another courſe, and is very ca<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>tious that his Language may in nothing offend them, ſtudying all manner of ways to pleaſe and accommodate himſelf to their manner of Behaviour; entertaining them with a New Song, or witty Paſſages, culled out of the neweſt Plays; and if he finds them in a briſk jolly Humour,
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:35213:36"/>then out comes a Lampoon, which he inſinuates was lately made on ſome Perſon of Quality; reads it, and cunningly ſkips over the Smutty or Bawdy part of it. Inſtead of ſpeaking in form of Syllogiſms and Pedantry, like things newly fluttered out of the Univerſity, and being but Pen-feathered in Under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding, come hopping to Town; he is wiſe to divert them with what they underſtand; tells them of a Ball, where ſuch and ſuch fine Ladies are to paſs the Evening, and what excellent New Play is to be acted to morrow; if he perceives them inclined to Melancholy, out comes his Flute or Violin; if they reſolve to be Serious, he is Complaiſant in that: If he ſees any wantonly inclined, he knows how to ſingle her out, and not give offence to the reſt; and can give her her Bellyful of Toying, from whom he quickly retires, for fear of cloying; for it is not to dwell too long at once in one Chamber, he ſeeks variety, and makes his Viſits accordingly; nor is he ſuffered to depart empty-handed, or it any be ſlack in rewarding his Service, he is furniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with a ſufficient ſtock of Impudence to frame a pretence to Borrow; or in toying ſlip a Diamond-Ring from the Finger, which he ſeems to take in Jeſt, but keeps in Earneſt. By this means he grows more gay and ſparkiſh, and as his trim Garniture is much taking in the Eyes of Amourous young Fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>males, ſo his well-timed Diſcourſe Charms their Ears, and raiſes Diverſion out of every ſmall Occur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence; when in one Scene he has given them all the Delight he is able, he is ſo prudent, leſt it grow tedious, to ſhift it to another, never continuing in one Humour ſo long 'till it become diſtaſtful: he is not ignorant that the choiceſt Delights ſooneſt Surfeit, and that continual feeding on one Diſh, though ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſo delicate, in time will nauſeate the Stomach;
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:35213:37"/>he therefore varies his Diverſion ſutable to the Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour of the Sex, which renders his Viſits acceptable, longed for, and his departure never without regret, 'till the upſhot comes, and they plainly ſee his whole Buſineſs has been to deceive. For if at any time they have a mind to be Treated, he Scruples not to do it with much Gallantry and Generoſity, as knowing how to reimburſe himſelf in the Concluſion: Out of this incloſed <hi>Seraglio</hi> he plays the Grand Seignor, Calls out one beſt pleaſing to him, or Richer than the reſt, waits on her to the Park, a Ball, or Play; in each of which he Infinitely pleaſes, giving her an opportunity to Expoſe her Beauty and Gallantry; but whilſt ſhe is endeavouring by all her Arts and Subtiltys to ſet her ſelf off for Sale, little thinks ſhe that he is practiſcing on her Eaſineſs and over-Cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulity, to ruin her in her Faine and Fortune; for Ten to One, that he may not tickle his Trout too long, and ſo run the hazard of loſeing her, he enflames her with Wine, into which he ſecretly conveys provoking Drugs in fine Ponder, not diſcernable in the Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quids, to heat her Blood, and heighten her Deſires; then by a ſmooth inſinuating Flattery, with delu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding Words, he corrupts her Judgment, and over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>powers her Conſcience, which made her before to ſtart at the Thoughts of any ſuch thing: So that with little Scruple an Aſſignation is made, and ſhe im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prudently Surrenders her Honour without Condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions; and from that moment he dates her Perſon and Fortune at his diſpoſal. And having Rooked her out of what he could himſelf, in Rings, Jewels, or Ready Money, but he either gives her the ſlip, and leaves her to lament at leiſure her haſty Folly, or puſhes her to be yet more miſerable, on ſome one of his Shabby Companions; under pretence of his being a Country Knight or Eſquire, who has a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderable
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:35213:37"/>Eſtate, keeps his Coach and Six, has a numerous Attendance to wait on him: And this Bargain is clapt up in Hugger-mugger, without the leaſt knowledge of her Relations or Friends; who no ſooner hear of it, but they caſt her o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>f, or if ſhe has any Fortune they cannot hinder her o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, her extravagant Huſband ſoon makes it fly; and then reſolving not to ſee her Want, makes up his Pack and Travels into <hi>Terra Incognita,</hi> and ſo left in a poor abandoned Condition, brought up too deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate to Labour, Temptations Prompt her from Ill to Worſe, laying a Stain on her Family, and a laſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Infamy on her ſelf.</p>
               <p>As he does by one, ſo he deals by all, but by dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent means; for there is as much variety of Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour, Inclination and Paſſion in Womankind, as there is in Man, and they muſt be accordingly wrought on by due Conformity, for advantage: though I ſhall not here go about (for it would be an endleſs labour) to diſcover all the Plots, Snares, Stratagems, Whims, Contrivances, Projects, Flat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teries and Inſinuations he uſeth himſelf, and by Proxy procures, to wriggle himſelf firſt into the good liking and affection of Young Gentlewomen and others; and having made himſelf Secretary of their Honour, he diſpoſes of their Reputation and Fortunes, according to his own Diſcretion, Building on a Foundation their Ruins, to brave it with the beſt. And now I ſhall conclude this Chapter, with ſome ſober Advice and Caution to young La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies and Gentlewomen, as to their Carriage and Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haviour, to avoid the Snare ſo frequently laid by Crafty Men, to intrap them at Unawares.</p>
               <p>To Men therefore you are to have a Behaviour that may ſecure you without offending them; no ill-bred affected Shineſs nor roughneſs, unſutable to
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:35213:38"/>your Sex, and unneceſſary to your Virtue; but ſuch a way of Behaviour as may prevent all coarſe Ralleries or unmannerly Freedoms; a Look that may forbid without Rudeneſs, and Oblige without Invitation, or leaving room for Mens ſawcy Infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rences to ſuggeſt advantages over you, or their Vanities ot lay hold on: for gaining the leaſt En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couragement, or Hope to Triumph over your Virtue. This point is ſo very nice, that it ought to engage you to have a perpetual Watch on your Eyes; con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidering that a careleſs Glance often gives more en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couragement than many Words; the Language of the Eyes is very Significant, and Cunning, Deſigning Men can interpret it to your Prejudice, and their own Advantage. Your Civility, which is always to be preſerved, muſt not be carried ſo high as a Compliance, which may Betray you into irrecovera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Miſtakes.</p>
               <p>Beware of the Vanity of deſiring to gain a Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt over Men, as ſome fooliſhly attempt to do; and like the Moth, burn themſelves in the Flames; nay think themſelves ſecure of not having their Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour tainted by it. Some are fondly apt to believe their Virtues obſcure, and not ſufficiently known, unleſs expoſed by a larger, or ſet out to the beſt advantage, by ſome publick Trials; but theſe are dangerous Experiments, and uſually fail, being built on the weak Foundation of too great a Confidence in themſelves. It is as dangerous to Play with Light<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, as to Dally with Gallantry. it is a Conſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring againſt your ſelves, and giving Treacherous Men a power to gain an eaſy Conqueſt; and from a pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tending Admirer, ſoon becomes Victor, and grows to be a Maſter over your Affections. The firſt reſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution of ſtopping at a good Opinion and Eſteem, by degrees grows weaker againſt the Charms of Inſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuation;
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:35213:38"/>and Flattery ſkilfully applied, you will be apt to think a Man ſpeaks to much Reaſon, whilſt he is Commending you, that you will have much ado to believe him in the wrong, when he is Craftily undermining you, and inſenſibly, as it were Steal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing away your Affections. And, over and above the natural Inclination your Sex has to be merciful, you are apt to be Bribed by a well-choſen Flattery, and ſo are in danger to be taken like a Bird liſtening to the Call of a Fowler, that has laid a Snare for it.</p>
               <p>Conqueſt is ſo tempting a thing, that it frequent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly makes you miſtake Mens Submiſſions, which with all their fair appearances, have generally leſs Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect than Art in them: Therefore let it be your Buſineſs, to remember where there is a ſly Inſinua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, without much Oſtentation of fine Words or Compliments, you are to ſuſpect a Deſign, to gain admittance under a Diſguiſe; therefore you ought to be upon your guard, and conſider, that of the two, Reſpect is more dangerous than Anger; it puts for a time the beſt Underſtandings out of their place, 'till ſecond Thoughts reſtore them; it ſteals inſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſibly upon you, and throws down your Defences, making it too late to Reſiſt after that advantage is is given: whereas Anger moſtly breaketh out into a found, and paſſing away in a noiſe, gives warn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to be Cautious; whilſt Reſpect is a ſlow, yet a certain Poiſon that ſwells you; and where it pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vaileth too much, it turns to a kind of Apoplexy in the Mind, turning it quite round; and after once it has ſeized the Underſtanding, becometh Mortal. For theſe Reaſons, the ſecureſt way is to Treat it like a ſly and crafty Enemy, and to be perpetually on the Watch, Guarded againſt it.</p>
               <p>To treat here of Reſervedneſs, would be too long, eſpecially to enumerate all the Advantages that at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:35213:39"/>it; therefore I ſhall only ſay it is a Guard to thoſe that are Virtuous of your Sex; and a Diſguiſe to ſuch as are Vicious: and of ſo much uſe to both, that thoſe who refuſe to practiſeit as a Virtue, ought to uſe it as an Artifice.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. VI.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>The Character of a <hi>Rake,</hi> and what Devices he uſes to Inſinuate into the Aquaintance of <hi>Maid-Servants;</hi> by what means he Plots their Ruin and Diſgrace, and how he is to be known, and avoided: with Sober Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice to all <hi>Servants</hi> of the Female Sex, and what elſe may be an advantage to them.</p>
               </argument>
               <p>I Now come to give Advice and Precaution to thoſe of the Female Sex that are of the lower Form, who are alſo liable to Temptations, and ſtand very tickliſh, if they are not fortified with a good ſtock of Prudence for their Guard: for theſe being more expoſed, and lying more open to Temptati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, than the foregoing, as being of eaſier acceſs, there are many that make it their Buſineſs to draw them into a Snare: for under this Head I ſhall treat of ſuch as are Servants, and plainly ſhew them their dangerous Enemy maſqued in the Diſguiſe of Friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip: and firſt I ſhall give his Character.</p>
               <p>His Parentage is as obſcure as the ſource of the River <hi>Nilus;</hi> for he was taken from his Mother, who had made a ſlip, by a Strowling Beggar for a ſmall Sum, and lugg'd about City and Country at her Back in a Blanket, 'till he was able to trudge after, like the Wild <hi>Iriſh,</hi> Bare-Footed; but growing up, her hard uſage made him give her the go-by, and endeavour to ſhift for himſelf, but <hi>Bridewell</hi> and the
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:35213:39"/>Whiping-Poſt, in time weaned him off the Begging Trade, and makes him bethink himſelf of creeping into ſome Inn, and getting into the Under-Oſtlers favour, turns Boot-cleaner, for which he is allow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed a Lodging under the Manger; and the Maid for ſome litte Drudgery he does in the Kitchen, feeds him with the Reverſion of Scraps, Drink he gets for running of Errands; but in time his Diligence be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing taken notice of, he is better encouraged, and riſes by degrees to be Under-Oſtler himſelf, or is put in ſome other vacancy, equivalent to it; and whilſt he behaves himſelf tolerably in that Station, his Miſtreſs perhaps caſts her Eye on him, and mark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his features and good ſhapes, lets ſtrange Whims run in her Head, that he is ſometing more than he ſeems, and concludes him to be of good Parentage; which induces her to Compaſſion, and to remove him from the offenſive Employ of turning up Horſe-Dunghils, to one more Gentile, <hi>viz.</hi> that of Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berlain, intruſting him with the clean Sheets! and Keys of the Chambers, poſſeſſed with a ſtrange Long<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to lye her ſelf in a Bed of his making. But be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing thus on a ſudden exalted from the Stable to the beſt Rooms in the Houſe, not able to manage the fortune of ſo unexpected a Favour, he all on a ſud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den grows Proud, Inſolent, and Talkative, on which account he is kicked out of Doors, and has once more the wide World to ſhift in: he caſts many things in his Mind, yet few give a proſpect to hit; at length, as he to paſs away the time, is talking with a Semſtreſs about ſome trivial matters, caſting his Head about all on a ſudden, and eſpying the counterfeit of his nutbrown Face in her Glaſs, he preſumptuouſly conceits himſelf more Charming than <hi>Adonis,</hi> or more lovely than <hi>Narciſſus;</hi> this vain conceit improves in his Fancy, and ſwells him into a
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:35213:40"/>belief that his Miſtreſs caſting her Eyes on him, was not the effect of Chance, but that he wears about him alluring Temptations, that no Female can reſiſt; and having heard it is a thriving way to ſuch as live on their eaſy Spoyls, it bolts into his Noddle to employ his Talent this way.</p>
               <p>Upon this occaſion, putting himſelf into the beſt Garb Fortune at preſent will afford him, he Saunters, caſting his Eye at every Shop or open Door, to mark out the Game he intends to make his Flight at: If he eſpies a neat Laſs, whereby he gueſſes ſhe well deſerves in her Service, and may be in Stock to anſwer in ſome meaſure his expectation, whether ſhe be intendant of the upper Stories, or Superviſor of the Dripping-pan, Chamber or Cook Maid, it matters not, for all is Fiſh with him that comes to Net: he ſtares her wiſhfully in the Face, and takes a turn or two backward and forward, as if he had ſome knowledge of her; or ſo as if he we<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e doubtful whether that knowledge was certainly grounded, or might prove a miſtake; and at that time goes away without any farther notice taken, yet fails not to put in at the next Ale-houſe, and makes all the Enquiry he can, yet with ſuch cauti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, that the Relators cannot dive into the meaning of it. What Intelligence he gets, he notes down in his Pocket Book, to help out his Treacherous Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mory at a dead lift: and if he is ſo lucky to get her Name, and what Country-breed ſhe is, he hugs him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, concluding he has gained a main Point; for he doubts not, if he by this means can come into her Company, to wheedle more out of her, ſo cun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ningly, that putting it into other words, ſhe ſhall Ten to One forget ſhe told it him, and in ſome amazement conclude he knows her better than ſhe thinks for; if after he be ſo lucky to be thereabout,
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:35213:40"/>when he ſees her go abroad, as on a Holyday, or the like, or ſent of an Errand, he paſſes her, turns back, and ſtares in her Face, and with a Smile, cryes O, Mrs. <hi>Betty</hi> or <hi>Molly,</hi> is it you! I thought I was not miſtaken but ſhould know you, though it is ſo long ſince I ſaw you. Upon this, he accoſts her with ſuch obliging Behaviour, that the Girl ſtands amazed, bluſhes, and gazes on him, dropping a Curteſy, and then breaking ſilence, ſays, Truly Sir, you muſt excuſe me, for I cannot call you to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrance. It may be not, replyes he, but are you not of ſuch a Country? to which ſhe readily anſwers yes; then he vows, ſince his coming to Town, hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſhe was in Service, but not knowing well where, he has made it his Buſineſs to enquire, and thought it was ſhe as he paſſed by the other day, but not being certain, would not be ſo bold as to come into the Shop; but ſince Fortune has been ſo kind as it were, to throw this happineſs upon his, he muſt intreat her to take a Glaſs of Ale and an Orange with him. If ſhe excuſes it, on the account of ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſty Buſineſs, or Coyneſs, as not well knowing what to think of the matter, he urges ſo many ſeeming Reaſons for it, and ſays he has ſomething to tell her from her Relations, worth her hearing, and not fit to be talked on in the Street, that at length ſhe has no Argument againſt his Perſwaſions.</p>
               <p>Being in the place he would be, he ſounds her Mind, about her like or diſlike to the City; and what Motives induc'd her to leave the Country, or what elſe he can gather from her; who marking his courteous Behaviour and profound Reſpect, at length ſhe ſhakes off her Scruples and Fears, growing more free and open with him; ſo that in a little time he comes to know the place of her Birth and Parentage, if ſhe knows it her ſelf. Then his next Buſineſs is
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:35213:41"/>to praiſe them to the Skys for their Honeſty and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duſtry, ſtill he perſwades her that he knew her and them, a long time. If ſhe ask his Name, he takes up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on him that of ſome noted Family in the Country, but at a pretty diſtance, leſt he ſhould be taken trip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping: and to be brief, after ſome ſoft pr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>gs of her Lips, he begins to change the Diſcourſe to that which is ſomewhat Amourous; demands how ſhe ſtards affected to Marriage, and whether ſhe be en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaged; and being reſolved in theſe, he proteſts him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, from the firſt time he ſaw her, had a kindneſs for her; and hearing ſhe had left the Country, it was one main Motive that brought him to <hi>London,</hi> where by Providence he is ſettled in a good Employ: but that nothing ſo joys his Heart, as that he is bleſſed in finding her out, which ſeems to him as if Heaven deſigned their happineſs. And by ſuch De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vices, ſtealing inſenſibly into the Maids unguarded Affections, ſhe ſcruples not for the future to meet him by appointment, or come to him, if her time will poſſibly give her leave, when he ſends for her. If at any time ſhe enquires into his Buſineſs, as to what Station he is in, he tells her he belongs to the <hi>Cuſtoms, Exciſe,</hi> or the like, but gives her no par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular Account, leſt the matter coming cloſer, her ſcrupuloſity ſhould put her upon the curioſity of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king an Enquiry which would not hold Water.</p>
               <p>And becauſe he has, or expects many to deal with on the like account, he puſhes on his diſſembled Love apace, preſenting her, the better to colour it, with ſome Trifles, and Treats of Cakes and Ale, when they walk abroad, to <hi>Hackney</hi> or <hi>Iſlington.</hi> And now his Proſpect begins to work, for Love corrupting her Judgment, and overpowering her Reaſon, he finds he has brought her to his Bent, and can mold
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:35213:41"/>her as he think <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>. The ſolemn Engagement of a ſpeedy Marriage is reciprocally given and taken; and then dreaming of nothing, but in a ſhort time to be a Miſtreſs; and firmly relying on the Fidelity of his Promiſes, bound with Vows and Oaths, T<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> to One (things not to be got quickly in a readineſs for Marriage, or her Time not up) he prevails with her to let him make a <hi>Pye-Corner</hi>-Enſurance upon her Belly, which Point if he can gain, he is confident ſhe will deny him nothing: he then takes an op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunity when he has heightned her in a loving Mood, to complain of Diſappointments in receiving Money, what great Advantages he is likely to loſe for want of it; and when he Lent it, he did not expect to be trifled with, but thought it had been ready Money at any time, when he ſhould call for it. Then out come Bills or Bonds, ſigned by we know not who, and he ſeems to fret like Gam'd T<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ff<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ty, to be ſo ungentilely uſed, when he lent it with ſo good a meaning, to do them a kindneſs; that Fifty Pounds are due to him, for his Sallary the Laſt-Quarter; and relying on that which never uſed to fad, has ſtreightned him. The eaſie loving Fool, blinded with Paſſion, preſently concludes, he wants this Money chiefly to provide things neceſſary for their Wedding, but is Aſhamed to own it, on that accompt freely offers what aſſiſtance ſhe can give him, and if all her ready Money ſeems not to ſatisfie him, ſhe will not ſtick upon the leaſt motion he makes, if ſhe be in credit, to Borrow of her Fellow-Servants; But as ſhe has been inſtructed, conceals from them to what end ſhe does it; however, after this he leaves not off making his Viſits, for he has yet ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Game to play, and under the notion of being her Coſin, has at length liberty to come to the Houſe, eſpecially privately, among the Servants; and then
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:35213:42"/>Bottles of Wine, Ale, or what the Houſe affords, are pinched at ſeaſonable times and ſet by, to Treat; and ſhe will not ſtick to ſpare the beſt Bit ſhe can Light on out of her own Belly, to put in his; who has, as ſhe ſuppoſes, been ſo king to her, and if there be a fear of ſurprize by the Maſter or Miſtreſs, that he may create Anger, ſhe has a By<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cloſet to hide him, or ſometimes for haſte per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps, Whelms him under a large Waſh-Tub or Brew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Veſſel, where he may peep through the half Bung-hole, like a Dog under a door, to ſee when the Coaſt is clear, though that ſhe is as careful of that as he, to give the hint, upon the firſt opportu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, to be packing.</p>
               <p>By this means he has an opportunity to ſee the ways of the Houſe, and if himſelf wants Courage to be actually concerned in the Undertaking, yet he is intelligent enough to give Directions to thoſe that will Rob it; and indeed many over-fond Girls have been drawn in to be conſenting to, and furthering ſuch Wickedneſs, at the coſt of their Lives, and the Diſgrace of their Relations; who had they not met with ſuch Seducers, would never have Dreamed of any thing like it. And of theſe, I could name many, whoſe hard Fates have been pittied and much lamented, as not properly their inclination or fault, but their misfortune. But being beſide my purpoſe, I omit the Relations.</p>
               <p>Well, by this time he has drained her of all the Coin ſhe has, or can borrow; his Viſits are there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſeldomer, and that excuſed by exceſs of Buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs: For by this time he has ſtarted freſh Game. When ſhe urges Marriage, he puts it off with de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lays, which ſo troubles her Spirit, that her Work is neglected, ſhe muſes often, and grows Melancholy: that quite changed from what ſhe was, her Miſtreſs
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:35213:42"/>Chides, and ſhe retorts, ſo that growing uneaſy, ſhe tells him of it at the next meeting; for ſhe other ways knows not where to find him if her Life lay at ſtake, hereupon he adviſes her to take what Wages are due to her, pack up her things, and he will provide her a Lodging till they can be Married, and better accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modated, ſaying, with a <hi>Judas</hi>-Kiſs, he will not have his Love ſo uſed, for he is able to maintain her at as good a rate, as her Maſter does her Miſtreſs.</p>
               <p>The poor deceived Girl takes this as a Mighty kindneſs, and punctually obeys him; then he con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veys her with her Luggage, to a Lodging he has pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided, where he is not known; telling the people before her face ſhe is his Wife; this makes her bluſh, but being ordered before not to deny it, ſince they are ſo by Promiſe, and ſhortly ſhall be legally joined, ſhe accords with him in it; and ſo for a while one Bed ſerves them both: but after a Week or two, he ſends her on a Sleeveleſs Errand, and paying off the Lodgings, companions of his own, in the Habit of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>orters carry off her Trunks, and what they contain; for he will be ſure not to let her go abroad that day in her beſt Apparel, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tending the Buſineſs ſo urgent, that ſhe muſt not ſtay to change. When ſhe returns, and perceives what has happened, ſhe is yet ſo credulous, that for ſome time ſhe will not believe the People rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting to it, nor her own Eyes, but having waited long, and perceiving it too true, ſhe burſts into Tears, wrings her hands, ſeeks up and down for him, but in vain; and then, which way to turn her ſhe knows not, the growing Burthen of her Womb brings her Folly perpetually into Remembrance; and in this miſerable State, aſhamed to appear amongſt her former acquaintance in <hi>London,</hi> if ſhe be of a high Mind and proud Spirit, to hide her ſhame
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:35213:43"/>from the F<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>es of all that know her, ſhe S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>lls her ſelf to the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>; if not, ſhe takes the Cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage to trudge it on foot, to be the firſt Relator of the unwelcom misfortune, to her Parents, and afflicts them as well as her ſelf: who however to ſave her Credit, give out ſhe is Married, but her Huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band is gone an <hi>Eaſt India</hi> Voyage, or ſome ſuch trivial Excuſe; which ſome believe, and others are Left to their Liberty; yet they keep the Child, and ſhe is ſent up with a new Recruit to Service, upon Solemn Promiſe to be Wiſe, at the rate of ſuch dear bought Experience; and in the end perhaps makes an honeſt poor Trades-man a Wife; who perhaps to his Lives end, knows no other than that he Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried a pure Virgin. And here I may ſay, her luck turns again, though to no great advantage.</p>
               <p>If he <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>inds ſome he would prey upon, too cunning to be catched in his Snare, <hi>viz.</hi> that they will come to no Terms without Marriage, if they are any thing Wealthy, he will condeſcend to that, but leave them in a little time. I knew one of theſe kind of Fellows, who was reported to have a D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>zen Wives at one time alive, that he was lawfully Married to; beſides many that he chouſed, under pretence of Courtſhip; and ſo lived at a tearing rate on their Spoils: And when any of them found him out, for he frequently Shifted, and threatened the Penalty of the Law, he would wheedle them into a Reconcilement; and uſe ſo many flattering Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guments, that he del<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ded them rather into new Follies, than to revenge the great injury he had d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ne.</p>
               <p>I ſhall conclude this Chapter with ſome Advice to Maidens, and that in matters of this nature. I wiſh them rather to be miſtruſtful than Credulous; Miſtruſt is the Sinew of Policy, for want of it many
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:35213:43"/>have been undone: know men well, before you let them into your Affections; not by ſeeing their Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, but by a ſtrict Enquiry where they were Edu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cated, who they are, and what their Converſation; Marriage, if it come to that, is a Buſineſs for Life, and one of the weightieſt in Temporal matters. Conſider then with what caution every one ought to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> towards it, but eſpecially to avoid the Company of ſuch as make it their Buſineſs, inſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſibly to entangle eaſie fond Creatures, to no other end, than their own Advantage, and the others Ruin. I think I have laid down a ſufficient num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of their crafty Tricks and Devices, to warn any reaſonable Perſon, to be too forward in giving countenance to ſuch Deceivers: And doubt not but the Judicious Reader will be bound to thank me for ſuch a Diſcovery; and ſo prudent as to avoid the dangerous Rocks, whereon ſo many have Shipwrackt their Fame and Fortune.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="chapter">
               <pb n="82" facs="tcp:35213:44"/>
               <head>CHAP. VII.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>The Artifices, Tricks, and Devices uſed by <hi>Shifts, Sharpers, Rooks, &amp;c.</hi> to Cheat and Bubble the Ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norant in Gaming; with ſober Advice to avoid it.</p>
               </argument>
               <p>AS for the Tricks and Cheats that the foregoing Miſcreants uſe in Gaming, eſpecially when they draw in Young People to Cheat and Bubble them out of their Money, they are ſo many and va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious, it would ſwell a large Volume to ſet them down in order; nor had I done it briefly, but to make good my Promiſe to the Reader.</p>
               <p>If they ſet upon you with Cards, in the firſt place, in their Dealing, by the Reflection of a Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhed Steel Tobaco-Box, or a drop of Wine or Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter before them on the Board, unminded by you, they will ſo order it, that they will ſee the Cards they deal you, and ſo Play by your Hand; and if it is objected, they cannot ſee the Colour of the Spots this way, it is eaſie however, to know them by their form.</p>
               <p>If the Pack paſſes but a few times about, they will mark all the Winning Cards, ſo to know them as the Game requires; ſecuring in the Sleeve, a Muff that lyes before them, or Cocking a pinched-up Hat is a uſual way; if all the Cards be not required to be out, ſome of theſe <hi>Sharpers</hi> have a Dog with them, that will bring Cards under the Table, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livered him ſecretly by a Confedrate on the other ſide, and carry back what is given him by his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter: They have Signs and Watch-words, ſo often changed, that few underſtand them but themſelves; Winking, Laughing, Drawing the Mouth to one ſide or other, Blowing the Noſe, rubbing the Forehead,
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:35213:44"/>Drinking more or leſs, Snuffing a Candle at once or twice, with many more; makes the Confederates underſtand what they are to do. The higheſt Trump or other Winning-Card they uſually ſecure in the Palm of the Hand, upon Dealing ſlide it under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt, or otherwiſe ſhow it to their advantages. If at <hi>Put</hi> one give you two Treys and Ace, to dare you to be bold, or to Double Stakes, doubt not but your Antagoniſt has two Treys and a Duce, to bite your Head off, as in their <hi>Cant</hi> they phraſe it. They of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten put the Change upon you, if they find your Memory treacherous, in taking up the Cards; under pretence of ſeeing what was Played. They fail not to have the Winning Cards of another Pack about them, and where they ſee an Opportunity, make uſe of them; and as cunningly withdraw them again, upon the Shuffling.</p>
               <p>Falſe Dice they always carry about them, which they ſecure in their Hand often, with the Chance uppermoſt; though they ſeem to the unſkilful Player to come out of the Box, and have an Art in Shaking, to rattle them as if they were really in; and when they have done Throwing, by ſlight of Hand, convey them away, and put the other to Throw with thoſe they produce. Sometimes they have them with Quick-ſilver ſhut up in a hollow of the corner, or in the Center, as the Chance is to run; which will hit to thoſe that know how to place them in throwing, but run croſs to the Game<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter that knows nothing of it; with much more of the like Nature: But my Deſign being to diſſwade from Gaming, I ſhall no farther enlarge on the Cheats practiſed in it, but conclude with ſome Sound Advice.</p>
               <p>To Play ſometimes, to divert ones ſelf; or en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertain civil Company, is not ſo much to be diſallow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed;
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:35213:45"/>but to do it ſo often, as to be called a Game<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter, is to be avoided; for then it looks more like Buſineſs than a Recreation; for it hath Conſequen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of ſeveral kinds, not to be endured. It will engage you into a habit of Idleneſs, and ill Hours, draw you unto ill mixed Company, make you ne<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect your Affairs abroad and at home.</p>
               <p>To Deep Play there will be yet greater Objecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons; it will give occaſion to the World to aſk ſpiteful Queſtions, how you dare venture to Loſe ſo much, and what Means you have to bear it cut; and beſides the Damage it does to your Credit, when it takes Air; if you could but ſee your Fa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> upon an Ill Game, at a deep Stake, you would cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly forſwear any thing that could put your Looks under ſuch a Diſadvantage.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:35213:45"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
